<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Allotrioepiskopos, the busie bishop. Or The visitor visited. By way of answer to a very feeble pamphlet lately published by Mr J.G. called Sion Colledge visited, in which answer, his cavils against the ministers of London for witnessing against his errours touching the holy Scriptures, and the power of man to good supernaturall, are answered, and the impertinency of his quotations out of the fathers, Martin Bucer, and Mr Ball are manifested. / By William Jenkyn minister of the Word of God at Christ-Church London.</title>
            <author>Jenkyn, William, 1613-1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 181 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87552</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J632</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E434_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202641</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862860</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862860</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115038</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87552)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115038)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 68:E434[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Allotrioepiskopos, the busie bishop. Or The visitor visited. By way of answer to a very feeble pamphlet lately published by Mr J.G. called Sion Colledge visited, in which answer, his cavils against the ministers of London for witnessing against his errours touching the holy Scriptures, and the power of man to good supernaturall, are answered, and the impertinency of his quotations out of the fathers, Martin Bucer, and Mr Ball are manifested. / By William Jenkyn minister of the Word of God at Christ-Church London.</title>
                  <author>Jenkyn, William, 1613-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 60 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.M. for Christopher Meredith at the Crane in Pauls-Church yard, and Tho. Vnderhill at the Bible in Woodstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to the work by John Goodwin.</note>
                  <note>First word of title in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March 30th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Goodwin, John, 1594?-1665. --  Sion-Colledg visited --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sion College --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Presbyterianism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115038:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ΑΛΛΟΤΡΙΟΕΠῚΣΚΟΠΟΣ The Buſie Bishop. OR The Viſitor Viſited. By way of Anſwer to a very feeble Pamphlet lately Publiſhed by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>J. G.</hi> called <hi>Sion Colledge viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> In which Anſwer, his Cavils againſt the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of <hi>London</hi> for Witneſſing againſt his Errours touching the holy Scriptures, and the power of man to good ſupernaturall, are anſwered, and the impertinency of his quotations out of the Fathers, <hi>Martin Bucer,</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Ball</hi> are manifeſted.</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM JENKYN Miniſter of the Word of God at Chriſt-Church <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Cum ex Scripturis arguntur haeretici in accuſationem convertuntur ipſarum Scripturarum, quaſi non rectè habeant, neque ſint ex <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utoritate, &amp; qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> variè ſint dictae &amp; quia non poſſit ex his inveniri veritas, ab his qui neſci. ant traditionem.</p> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iren lib.</hi> 3. <hi>adv. haereſ.</hi> cap, ſc.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Haeretici Scripturarum Lucifugae</p> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Tert. de reſur. carn.</hi> cap. quadrag. ſept.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>—nec habet quilquam quo ſurgere poſſit</l>
               <l>Ad vitam ſacro niſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urſum naſcitur or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p. de ingrat.</hi> cap. 15.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>—non moribus illi (ſcil. gratiae)</l>
               <l>Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mora, non cauſis anceps ſuſpenditur ullis.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A.M</hi> for <hi>Chriſtopher Meredith</hi> at the Crane in Pauls. Church yard, and <hi>Tho. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder hill</hi> at the Bible in Woodſtreet. 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:115038:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115038:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER: More eſpecially to the REVEREND AND LEARNED SUBSCRIBERS Of the late TESTIMONY to the TRUTH of CHRIST within the Province of LONDON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend and Beloved,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Hould the <hi>witneſſes to truth</hi> want ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, they might juſtly queſtion the truth of that to which they <hi>witneſſe.</hi> The <hi>Father of lies</hi> was not well pleaſed with your late teſtimony to the truth; He hath expreſt his diſlike of it with <hi>much rage,</hi> though (bleſsed be God) with more weakneſse: Never was an <hi>Overſeer</hi> ſo <hi>overſeen,</hi> as was this <hi>Biſhop</hi> in his late <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation of Sion Colledge,</hi> His Pamphlet ſpeaks him <hi>buſy,</hi> but yet more <hi>blinde</hi> then <hi>buſy:</hi> He might with leſſe diſgrace have contain'd himſelf within his <hi>darker dioceſſe:</hi> I mean the <hi>alley</hi> where he preacheth his <hi>errours.</hi> His weaker eyes like thoſe of the <hi>night-bird</hi> would have well endured <hi>that ſhady refuge:</hi> but adventuring upon the <hi>wings</hi> of his late Pamphlet, to oppoſe his <hi>feeble ſight</hi> to the <hi>Sun of truth ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> forth in the <hi>teſtimony;</hi> he diſcovers ſuch a <hi>dazeled and
<pb facs="tcp:115038:3"/>unable eye</hi> to guide the courſe of his wings, that I accounted it a matter of no difficulty for any to chaſe and catch him in an anſwer. His ambition made him ſo eager of putting out an anſwer <hi>to many men,</hi> that he took no care at all to put out an anſwer to one <hi>queſtion;</hi> His other writings are below the <hi>moſt,</hi> but this laſt peece was below <hi>himſelf.</hi> Account it not therefore ambition <hi>(Reverend Sirs)</hi> that puts the weakeſt of your numbers upon undertaking him. For the moſt of you, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> have performed this task, I ſhould have accounted it an act of (not to ſay too) <hi>great condeſcention.</hi> I finde not to my remembran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e throughout his papers, one quotation taken out either of <hi>Scriptures, Fathers, or modern writers,</hi> pertinently applied: nor any thing like an argument to prove the thing he undertakes to ſhew <hi>viz.</hi> why <hi>his</hi> opinions ſhould not be charged as erroneous. But this his double defect he ſupplieth with abundant rage in oppoſing Christ in his <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, grace, Miniſters, government,</hi> his rage against the two laſt reaching up to heaven, out of multitudes of inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that might be given, take but two, out of his Pamphlet.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> Concerning the government which the ſubſcribers ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of, he ſaith, That <hi>the <hi>beſt</hi> ſucceſſe which with any colour of truth,
<note place="margin">Sion Col. <hi>viſited</hi> p. <hi>26.</hi>
                  </note> we can entitle the Presbyterian govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unto, is</hi> to <hi>ſnipp and keep under thriving branches:</hi> I know he means not <hi>branches</hi> that thrive in <hi>hereſies,</hi> but clearly intends ſuch <hi>branches</hi> as <hi>thrive</hi> in <hi>holineſſe:</hi> The Lord ſmite his conſcience, and touch his heart for this expreſsion before it be wounded ſo as it will be beyond cure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Concerning the <hi>Reverend Miniſters of Chriſt</hi> in the city,
<note place="margin">Sion Col. <hi>viſited</hi> p. <hi>19.</hi>
                  </note> he ſaith, They <hi>Foment diviſions, Multiply diſtractions, Obſtruct the quiet compoſure and ſetling of things in the land</hi> (ſpeaks not my Lord just as if he were in his viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) and recompence <hi>no degree of all this unworthineſſe with <hi>any</hi> conſiderable</hi>
               </hi> good, would any Atheist in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:115038:3"/>have ſaid more? The genuine paraphraſe is, The Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters are the troublers and Traitors of the Kingdome, All their labours though never ſo ſucceſſefull <hi>in converting</hi> and building up of ſouls, amount not to the leaſt <hi>conſiderable good.</hi> The Kingdome might well be without them, and they do more hurt then good; And all this becauſe they cannot conform to his <hi>apiſh inventions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That dear reſpect which I bear to your calling and graces, to your late <hi>teſtimony for the truth,</hi> I might add to that ſweet and gracious converſe I have enjoyed and do frequently pertake of from you (particularly ſome of you that are members of that <hi>Claſſis</hi> where providence hath caſt me) Eſpecially (if my heart be not the greateſt liar in the world) The love I bear to the <hi>Lord Jeſus, who hath loved me and given him ſelf for me,</hi> and who is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſufferer of us all, by this <hi>impure Pamphlet,</hi> put me upon expreſsing my ſelf in this endeavour to ſerve you, I know not whether this buſy Biſhop intends to afford us a ſecond viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, If he doth, I hope he will come without invitation and be entertained without welcome even as a buſy-body. As for the reproaches of his meerly miſled followers, whether I eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape them, or ſuſtain them, I ſhall labour to bleſse God and love them being aſſured ſhould I have their stroke it would bein the dark by reaſon whereof a friend is ſometimes strook in ſtead of afoe; but when they have (I ſay not a new but) their old light) they will love me both again, and the more for ſuch a blinde unkindeneſſe. Som of them I know and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionately love for whom my hearts deſire is that they may be ſaved: I deſire them to know that I deſire to ſay <hi>I can die, I cannot be ſilent, when the truths are ſtruck at which I wiſh not to out-live;</hi> My hearty requeſt to them is like that of <hi>Moſes</hi> to the <hi>People, that they would depart from the tents of this man,</hi> if his Preaching be like his writing;
<pb facs="tcp:115038:4"/>that they would not feed upon chalk and coals in corners when the <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> hath provided them <hi>Paſtors after his own heart,</hi> and remember that under Praelacy they hated thoſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines as hell which now they advance to Heaven, and that then they ſpent daies of fasting againſt thoſe opinions which now they ſpend Sabbaths in hearing.</p>
            <p>For acrimony if any they finde, I deſire them not to be offended,<hi rend="sup">1</hi> Its leſſe then he deſerved,<hi rend="sup">2</hi> more then ever I did besto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upon all the men in the world beſides him ſelf put together,<hi rend="sup">3</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the uſing of it this charitable conſtruction may be put, that I lookt not upon him (though ſome doe) as past recovery, My work in this ſhort Treatiſe, was to anſwer h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt the Miniſters, for their tranſcribing his Errours, in their <hi>Teſtimony.</hi> My book would have ſwolne into a large volume, had I handled the Points according to their own extent, and according to the helps afforded by our Divines. But I hope I have done enough, to ſhew that he had no cauſe to complain of the Miniſters tranſcriptions, and that all his pretended allegations out of the <hi>Fathers, Bucer</hi> and M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ball,</hi> help him not at all, but rather ſpeak againſt him. My multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied occaſions have hindered me from ſo <hi>ſpeedy and large an Anſwer</hi> as may be expected, but as it is, Reverend and belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved friends, you have it and my ſelf to ſerve you in the things of Christ</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>WILLIAM JENKYN.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Study at Chriſt Church</hi> Load:</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Page 4. marg. read <hi>Paul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s voluit.</hi> p 8. marg. l 30. read <hi>de Chriſto</hi> l. 35. c. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> p. 8. l 23. r <hi>upheld</hi> p. 20. l 23. r. <hi>wherein (you ſay) &amp;c.</hi> p <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. l ult. r. <hi>tells m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it is to, &amp;c,</hi> p 23. l. 34. r. <hi>it is from God, written.</hi> p. 31. marg. r <hi>abijcere poſſit</hi> p. 41. l. 24 r. <hi>(and that truly)</hi> l. 11. r. <hi>you did ſpeak to, &amp;c.</hi> p. 45. l. 33. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>jutorium.</hi> p. 48 marg r. <hi>contendunt.</hi> p 52. marg. r <hi>Bacer. in Iob</hi> 6.44. p. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. l, 32. r <hi>with, the fathers,</hi> p. 52, marg r. <hi>eteſiph.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115038:4"/>
            <head>ΑΛΛΟΤΡΙΟΕΠῚΣΚΟΠΟΣ OR The Buſie Bishop.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>ELIGION never had greater enemies then thoſe of her own houſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sion Coll.</hi> viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. <hi>p.</hi> 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And a little after.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It was never well with RELIGION, ſince the Miniſters,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Your work is to <hi>kill Religion,</hi> but your way to do ſo,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> I perceive, is to <hi>kiſſe</hi> it. You ſeem to make towards the <hi>lips</hi> of Religion, but your aim is at her <hi>fifth rib:</hi> You advance her <hi>head</hi> in your Preface, but 'tis to break her <hi>neck</hi> in your book. In the pretence of your Preface you raiſe up Religion to the <hi>clouds:</hi> In the performance of your book you lay it among the <hi>clods;</hi> for muſt not <hi>Religion</hi> needs fall to the ground when her <hi>foundation</hi> upon which ſhe ſtands is pluckt away? And takes not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e away the <hi>foundation of religion,</hi> who denies the Scripture to be that <hi>foundation?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Div. Authority of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>p.</hi> 18.</note> And doth not <hi>John Goodwin</hi> deny the <hi>Scripture</hi> to be that <hi>foundation of Religion?</hi> What elſe is the Engliſh of theſe words, <hi>in terminis,</hi> his own, <hi>viz. Queſtionleſſe no writing whatſoever, whether tranſlations or originals are the foundation of Chriſtian Religion;</hi> Away with your hypocriticall exclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115038:5"/>againſt the enemies of <hi>Religion,</hi> and your Crocodiles tears in that <hi>Religion</hi> cannot be well for the <hi>Miniſters;</hi> were your wit but hair to keen as your will, we ſhould in a ſhort time nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have <hi>Religion</hi> nor <hi>Minister</hi> left among us.</p>
            <p>But to your <hi>stuff.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The greateſt enemies to Religion are in her own houſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſit. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>Anſw.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>True, <hi>For of your own ſelves</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul) ſhall men ariſe ſpeaking penverſe things, to draw away Diſciples after them.</hi> Act, 20.30. And if of all that are in Religions own houſe, heretikes be her greateſt enemies, What will become of <hi>John Goodwin?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It was never well with Christian Religion, ſince the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Gospel (ſo called by themſelves,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſit. <hi>p</hi> 1.</note> and ſo reputed by others for want of knowing better) cunningly vested that privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Church of being the pillar and ground of truth in themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> For the <hi>Lectio.</hi> Your meaning, I ſuppoſe was, and had not rage againſt the Miniſters made you write non-ſenſe, you would have ſaid thus; <hi>The Miniſters cunningly veſted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in or with the priviledge of the Church,</hi> and not as you doe, <hi>The Miniſters veſted the priviledge of the Church in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves;</hi> A man may be veſted in, or with a priviledge, but it's very improper to ſay a priviledge is <hi>veſted</hi> in or with a man, as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper as to ſay a garment is veſted in the man that wears it: twere better to ſay the man is veſted in the garment; Its a ſign your pen is drunk with madnes, it doth ſo ſtagger and ſtammer; Theſe faults of pure weakneſſe, I ſhould not regard, did I obſerve either humility in you, under the ſenſe of greater in yourſelf, or ingenuity in you, in paſſing by ſmaller in others. But why finde I fault with the <hi>veſt,</hi> the phraſe of your book? The <hi>duſty cloaths</hi> of your words, are good enough for the crooked <hi>carcaſſe</hi> of your matter;
<note place="margin">This is <hi>Titu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bare in limite.</hi>
               </note> for I may well call the matter <hi>crooked;</hi> if to be true be to be ſtraight, for I finde two abominable falſities within the ſpace of two lines.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That the Miniſters of the Goſpel, are only ſo reputed by men, for want of knowing and conſidering better.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That they have vested themſelves with the priviledge of being the ground and pillar of truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>You ſay theſe Miniſters of the Gospel are only ſo reputed for want of conſidering better.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:115038:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. 'Tis your ſorrow to ſee, that they are ſo much as repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Miniſters, But Sir, 'tis your ſin to ſay, they are no more then Miniſters reputed. If they be no Miniſters, why diſprove you not their calling? Why bring you not an argument in ſtead of a ſcoff againſt them? But you may write thus with much praiſe from your deluded followers, and little pains to your feeble ſelf.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Tell me of one man, either Miniſter, or private Chriſtian, differing from the ſubſcribers only in the point of <hi>Independency,</hi> who dares ſay thus with you? I have heard ſundry of the <hi>Synodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call diſſenters</hi> preach, and profeſſe the contrary.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Or are you now got a ſtep or two above Independency? ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge you any Miniſters of the Goſpel at all, whether your ſelf, or any other? I obſerve, that you, who were wont to ſtile your ſelf, The <hi>Miniſter of a Church</hi> (ſuch an one as 'tis) <hi>in Colemanſtreet;</hi> now in this laſt Pamphlet, as if you had a minde to be lookt upon under another conſideration, word your ſelf only <hi>Iohn Goodwin, a ſervant of God and men,</hi> (I am ſure of men, I doubt whether of God) haply the <hi>Delilah</hi> of a Congregation hath entiſed you, to be tampering with the lock of our <hi>Miniſtery;</hi> you have yeelded already to caſt off the word Miniſter, by the next you may have caſt off the <hi>thing</hi> too.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If you do account your ſelf a Miniſter, I pray tell me in your next, which way you had your Ordination, whether by that way which the Miniſters of <hi>London</hi> had theirs, who you ſay are no Miniſters at all, or whether you had it by a <hi>Culinary</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in one of your allies. You tell the ſubſcribers afterward, of ſacred unction in a jeer, but know that no unction is the leſſe ſacred, for not coming out of the kitchin.</p>
            <p>Secondly, You ſay, The <hi>Ministers have vested themſelves with the priviledge of the Church, of being the ground and pillar of truth, and it was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ver happy ſince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I know not whether you who ſubvert the whole Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, intend not alſo to pervert this.
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.15.</note> By the <hi>Church</hi> her being the ground, <hi>and pillar of truth,</hi> all the Orthodox agree to be meant, the <hi>Church</hi> her maintaining and holding forth the truth; now the Church holds up, and holds forth the truth, either in a way <hi>common</hi> to all Chriſtians, mutuall exhortations, a way of profeſſion, and practice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or in a way peculiar to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome, a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteriall
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115038:6"/>way, of preaching the Word, adminiſtration of the Sacraments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If you ſay the Miniſters have <hi>vested</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the priviledge of being the <hi>pillar and ground of truth the first way,</hi> 'tis ridiculouſly falſe, profeſſion of the truth being common to the community, every one in the Church. If you mean (as you muſt needs) that, Miniſters have veſted themſelves with the priviledge of <hi>pillars,</hi> in the ſecond reſpect, <hi>viz.</hi> of Miniſtery, 'tis odiouſly falſe, for the <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and not themſelves, <hi>veſted</hi> them with the priviledge of holding forth <hi>truth</hi> by way of <hi>Office:</hi> Chriſt gave ſome <hi>Paſtors, and teachers,</hi> Eph. 4.11. <hi>God hath ſet ſome in his Church.</hi> 1 Cor. 12.38. And if in this reſpect, you intend that religion is ſo miſerable, becauſe all in the Church may not preach the Word, adminiſter Sacraments, and becauſe Miniſters do, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Speak out, Sir; It follows not, becauſe the Church holds forth the truth, therefore that all may hold it forth as Miniſters in it. Learned <hi>Calvin</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Galeſt is ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia ſoliue E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae miniſte. vio cenſerva tur. Quantum ergo onus paſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o vibas incumb t, quitam inaeſti mabilis theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>u <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>icuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>odiae pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt? Pau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> volnit prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſita off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> magnitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e, admoaito; eſſe paſtores qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>td illu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, diligentiâ, reveren ia al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini, lrare debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onr.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Etenin quam borribilis ſutura eſt ultio ſi eorii cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>pi intercidat veritas; Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> enin ideo col<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>na eſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatis, quia ſuo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iniſterio can tuetur, as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagat. Ergo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logium boc al miniſteriun verbi refertur quo ſublato con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Dei veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Suſtinetur Dei veritas p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra Evangel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> praed cattane.</hi> Calv. <hi>in</hi> 1 <hi>Tint.</hi> 3.15.</p>
               </note> upon this place, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. will inform you better, by whom, and what the Church, in that place of <hi>Timothy,</hi> maintains and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves the truth; Weigh the quotation, <hi>Quantum onus ergo</hi> &amp;c. how great a burden (therefore) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eth upon the Paſtors, who are to keep ſo ineſtimable a treaſure as the truth! <hi>Eccleſia ideo,</hi> &amp;c. Therefore is <hi>the Church</hi> the <hi>pillar, and ground of truth,</hi> becauſe ſhe defends it with the <hi>Miniſtery of the word.</hi> And <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium hoc,</hi> &amp;c. This commendation is to be referred to the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of the word,</hi> which being taken away, the truth fals. The truth is ſuſtained by the pure preaching of <hi>the Word.</hi> And the ſubſcribers their miniſteriall zeal for the truth both in preſſe and pulpit, is the occaſion of your rage againſt them; I confeſſe you may have a further aim, <hi>viz.</hi> to gratifie your deluded followers, whoſe deſign is to <hi>raze and levell the Church of Christ,</hi> and to preach, as well, as <hi>John Goodwin</hi> (as indeed they may ſoon do;) but the main ground of your rage againſt theſe holy men, is, becauſe they diſcover your errours. You ſtrike at the lanthorn, becauſe of the candle in it. At the pillar, becauſe of the proclamation, the Goſpel that hangs upon it. At the ſhepherds becauſe they defend their flocks. Were it not for theſe Miniſters, you would do well enough (you think) with the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115038:6"/>people; mean while remember, <hi>Omnis Apoſtata eſt oſor ſui ordinis,</hi> Religion never had greater enemies then rene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gadoes</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Miniſters of the Goſpel claim Nebuchadnezzars prere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative among men, over the truths of God,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sion Col</hi> viſited p. 1.</note> Whom he would he ſlew, whom he would he ſaved alive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> are among your ſelves.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> You have his <hi>Palace, A Babel,</hi> for ſuch is your way, His <hi>property, pride,</hi> far ſurmounting your <hi>Palace,</hi> and take heed, <hi>even you in particular,</hi> leſt his <hi>portion</hi> be alſo yours; The heart <hi>of a beaſt</hi> given unto you by God, for abuſing the <hi>heart of a man,</hi> For the truths of God ſlain by the Miniſters, I know none, unleſſe you mean <hi>old hereſies,</hi> lately vampt in your <hi>alley,</hi> for <hi>new truths,</hi> where, what ever is ſtrange, <hi>is true.</hi> O the patience of the God of <hi>truth,</hi> to ſuffer you to voice prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>hereſies,</hi> the truths of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo entitle the <hi>true God</hi> to ſo many <hi>untruths</hi> againſt <hi>God,</hi> Thoſe which you call truths, and yet ſay are ſlain by the miniſters, will continue errours, till you prove the contrary; And whereas you ſay that the Miniſters ſlay them, did the word ſpare them the Miniſters would do ſo too, who dare do nothing againſt the truth, but for the truth, and for their ſaving ſome errours alive, I pray prove what thoſe errours are, and the next edition of the teſtimony will not be wanting in due ſeverity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I wiſh nothing to the Ministers but good.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sion Col viſi.</hi> p 1. <hi>Anſ.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Devout ſoul that can curſe and bleſſe in one breath!</hi> Two lines off you blaſted the Miniſters with the title of <hi>murderous Nebuchadnezzars,</hi> and here you bleſſe them with deſires of all good to them; but whereas you ſay, you wiſh nothing in your praier, but good to the Miniſters. I fear you do nothing in your preaching, but hurt to the people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I wiſh the Miniſters had been in print without their own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or conſent.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on Col.</hi> viſi. p. 1. <hi>Anſ.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Your grief is not that the book was printed with their, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out your conſent: however the Miniſters are bound, to interpret charitably, this wiſh of yours, that they had been in print without their conſent, becauſe you your ſelf have ſped ſo well, by being in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115038:7"/>print without your conſent, when your Church ſet forth that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ridioulous paper, in commendation of you, wherein they extold you to the clouds (where, indeed, you alwaies are, when you write) Then you were in print againſt your conſent; the verſes put under your effigies, which ſay, that you have the perfections of ten thouſand men gathered in you, this was againſt your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent too I warrant you; I take care how the Authour will get into your favour again.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>So I might maintain honourable thoughts of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſited <hi>p.</hi> 1.</note> which I have alway laboured to doe, my witneſſe is o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> high.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is your witneſſe on high?
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> So is your Judge too, but take heed your puniſhment be not below: mock not God, nor deceive your ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Though I am ſtill oppoſed by them in my way.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>p.</hi> 2. <hi>Anſ.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>You cannot ſay that you have been oppoſed by them in Gods way; and 'tis a mercy for you to be oppoſed in your own way; your way is the way of <hi>Balaam,</hi> and it was an Angel that ſtopt him in his way.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Image ſtampt upon the Testimony, and the men whoſe names are affixed,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſited <hi>p</hi> 2.</note> are very unlike: the names ſubſcribed are learned and pious, but it bears the Image of weak and unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the <hi>ſubſcribers</hi> be <hi>learned and pious,</hi> I fear they are as unlike you,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> as you ſay they are unlike their own Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</p>
            <p>But if their Teſtimony be not for <hi>piety and learning</hi> like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, truly friend this your work is for impiety and ignorance, juſt like you, a thing upon which, <hi>John Goodwin fecit,</hi> need never be written; And yet the firſt ſide in your late book, againſt the Authority of the Scriptures, in my apprehenſion was very unlike you. I mean the verſes under your picture, which are a very jeer to you. The verſes ſay, that in you are gathered the perfections of ten thouſand men, with their gifts and graces, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny know, that you have more hereſies and errours, met in you, then are diſperſed among ſome thouſands in the world, and if your here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies (unles you are lately impoveriſhed) could be bequeathed to ten thouſand ſectaries, they might every one have a childes portion,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115038:7"/>and have ſufficient to live like ſuch men, when you are dead and gone. It was therefore a paſſage, as pernicious, as proud, which dropt from your pen in your Epiſtle, to your book called, The di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Authority of Scriptures, where you ſay, that you will endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, when you are gone, <hi>that your followers may have your ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit among them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> A ſingle portion of it would be far too much.
<note place="margin">Rom 12.2.</note> 'Twere better it might be transformed while you live, then be transmigrated when you die.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Ministens book is a Teſtimony againſt the truths of Joſus Chriſt, It teſtiſieth against this pretious truth of Jeſus.</hi> viz.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sion Col viſi. p.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>No writing whatſoever, whether originals or tranſlations, are the foundation of Chriſtian religion, wheneas this is aſſerted for a truth by the great Apoſtle.</hi> 1 Cor. 3.11. <hi>Other foundation can no man lay but Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tis a mercy that ſince you have ſo little of integrity,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> you have no more of intellect. Think you your ſelf able to woo th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Scrip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>res to afford you weapons againſt themſelves? Can you prove out of the Scripture, that there is no Scripture? You ſay <hi>Chriſt is the only foundation, therefore not the Scripture.</hi> But doth the one hinder the other? May not Chriſt be the only <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi> in point of <hi>mediation,</hi> and the Scripture in point of <hi>mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation and diſcovery?</hi> May not Chriſt be the foundation upon which, I build for <hi>ſalvation,</hi> and the Scripture the foundation upon which I ground the <hi>knowledge</hi> of this <hi>Saviour?</hi> I pray an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; Whether do you ground your knowledge, and belief that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the only <hi>foundation</hi> of ſalvation, upon this your cited place, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Other foundation,</hi> &amp;c? If you do not, why do you alledge it to prove that Chriſt is the only <hi>foundation?</hi> If you do ground your belief of <hi>Chriſt</hi> his being the only <hi>foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> upon this place, why do you bring this Scripture to prove, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> his being the <hi>foundation,</hi> hinders the Scripture from being ſo? Is it poſſible, that the known diſtinction of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſendi,</hi> and <hi>eng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſcendi, principium quod, &amp; quo,</hi> or a foundation <hi>perſonall,</hi> and <hi>ſcripturall,</hi> ſhould be bid from the eyes of this ſeducer in chief? Therefore do I acknowledge the Scriptures to be the <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi> of religion, becauſe they are appointed by God for the ſole manifeſtation of his will, concerning our ſalvation by Chriſt: we building our confidence that Chriſt is the only Saviour, upon
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115038:8"/>the Scripture which ſaith ſo. Is my dependence upon a friend for a favour, any hinderance to me from building my confidence upon his word alſo? nay do I not therefore build any hopes upon him, becauſe upon his word, his word revealing his will? you do wickedly therefore and weakly to oppoſe <hi>Christ,</hi> and his word; Give me one proteſtant writer that ever argued thus with you, The <hi>word</hi> is not our foundation, becauſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> is ſo, I am ſure the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.20. that we are built upon the <hi>foundation of the Prophets and Apoſtles</hi> (that is, their doctrine) and yet <hi>Chriſt</hi> was the <hi>corner ſtone</hi> for all that. If you doubt whether by the <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Prophets and Apoſtles,</hi> be meant their doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Chriſt:</hi> Conſult our learned and judicious expoſitours of that place.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quin funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> pro doctrina ſuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>è du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um eſt, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uim patriarch as nomin at aut p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> reges, ſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſolos qui offi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> habehant docen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> locet Poulue fidem Eccleſie in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ac doctrin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> debere eſſe fundatam,</hi> Calv. <hi>in loc. Doctrinam A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolorum &amp; prophetarum fundamento ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dificij compara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſc <hi>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oc. Nos affirmam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſundamentu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> illud quo niti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur eccleſiae fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des eſſe doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam prophetica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Apoſtolica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de Ceriſto</hi> Rol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loc <hi>in loc.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Chryl <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n loe. Paulus per A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolorum fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentum, doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Apoſto. lorum intelligit</hi> Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. <hi>Q</hi> 2. <hi>con.</hi> 4 <hi>de Monarch</hi> Pet. p 55<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Vid Chamier, de Canone. lib.</hi> 6. cap. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Calvins</hi> words are <hi>Quin fundamentum hic pro dec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinâ ſumatur minime dubiumeſt:</hi> and there's no doubt (ſaith he) <hi>hut the foundation of the Prophets, and Apoſtles, is here put for doctrine:</hi> Paul <hi>names not here the Patriarchs, or godly Kings, but thoſe only who had the office of teaching, and the faith of the Church is founded upon their doctrine.</hi> Thus far <hi>Calvin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In like manner, <hi>Piſcator, who ſaith, that</hi> Paul <hi>compareth the doctrine of the Apoſtles and Prophets to the foundation of a houſe. See alſo what that learned Scot,</hi> M. Rolloc <hi>ſaith upon the place: We affirm that the foundation upon which the faith of the Church is updeld, is the doctrine of the Apoſtles and Prophets of Chriſt, To the ſame purpoſe alſo Chryſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtome; and</hi> in their <hi>Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, the learned Whitaker</hi> and <hi>Chamier,</hi> who will inform you, if underſtood.</p>
            <p>You complain that this paſſage of yours is ranked among infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, and pernitious errours, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it is no foundation of Chriſtian Religion, to believe that the Scriptures are the word of God. Believing</hi> (you ſay) <hi>of the Scriptures is an act of man, Now no act of man is the foundation of Chriſtian religion; Only Chriſt is the foundation,</hi> 1 Cor. 3.11.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In that place of <hi>Hagiom.</hi> out of which this infamous errour is taken, you deal craftily, or (which is moſt like) cloudily, for your aim was to prove him guiltleſſe, who denieth the being of the Scriptures, and not that forbeareth the believing of them. For your argument, Chriſt is the <hi>foundation,</hi> and therefore not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115038:8"/>any act of man, as the beleeving of the Scriptures, 'tis very falſe and feeble: for though no act unto which man is enabled by God (ſuch as beleeving) is a foundation in that ſenſe in which Chriſt is upon whom we build the hope of our ſalvation to be obtained by his mediation, Yet, beleeving of the Scriptures as it is an aſſenting to a main and prime <hi>Credendum,</hi> viz. that <hi>the Scriptures are by divine inſpiration,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arg lib</hi> 1. <hi>de doct. Chriſt. cap.</hi> 37. <hi>Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ubabit ſides ſi ſcripturarum divinarum va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collabit authe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas.</hi>
               </note> is a neceſſary foundation for other ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent graces that are required in the Chriſtian Religion, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which foundation all godlineſſe and religion would in a ſhort time fall to the ground; no theologicall grace can be without ſaith, and faith cannot ſtand, if the authority of the Scriptures fall.</p>
            <p>If beleeving can be no foundation of Chriſtian religion, why doth the holy Ghoſt give to faith the name of foundation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1. In theſe words, not laying again the foundation of repentance from dead works and <hi>of Faith towards God,</hi> none will deny that the beleeving the Scriptures to be the word of God, is both the ground and an <hi>effentiall</hi> part of a right <hi>faith towards God.</hi> And therefore if the Apoſtle calleth <hi>faith towards God</hi> a <hi>foundation,</hi> he muſt needs imply that <hi>faith</hi> towards the <hi>Scriptures</hi> is a <hi>founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>You cavill at the Miniſters for ſaying they testifie to the truth and to their ſolemn league and covenant;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>p.</hi> 3.</note> do they mean</hi> (ſay you) <hi>that they give the ſame teſtimony to their ſolemn league and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant which they do to the truth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I obſerve your ſcornfull eſtranging expreſſion,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Their Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant:</hi> You diſclalm it, it ſeems, you had as good to throw it off in your lines as in your life:</p>
            <p>The <hi>Covenant</hi> is the Sectaries <hi>Shiboleth,</hi> he cannot ſpeak it plain; you deal with the Covenant as the Spaniel with the water, when you were ſwimming for your lives, it did bear you up, but now you are got to ſhore (ſafe as you think) you ſhake it off. Why is it that throughout this Section you do ſo under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>value the covenant? Is it for the good it hath done to the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, or the hurt you fear it may do to you? or do you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to make it break becauſe you cannot make it bend, and change as often as your intereſt doth?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But to your queſtion, do the Ministers give the ſame testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to the Covenant that they do unto the truth of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:115038:9"/>
            <p>I ſuppoſe you love to teſtifie much alike to both. As for the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, you cannot inforce an equalizing or a prelation of either to other out of theſe their words. <hi>And to our ſolemn league and covenant: AND</hi> was wont to be a note <hi>copulative</hi> not <hi>comparative.</hi> And yet I ſuppoſe the Miniſters teſtifie with the ſame integrity and unfainedneſſe to the one with which they do to the other.</p>
            <p>But note this zealot Paramount for the truths of Chriſt, he who by denying the Scriptures fears not to deſtroy the word of truth, thinks his ears defiled when with the covenant the Miniſters do but name the word (Truth) Like the hypocriticall Phariſees who feared not to be murderers of Chriſt, and yet were afraid of <hi>defilemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by going into the Hall,</hi> Joh. 18.28.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I know not what teſtimony the Covenant is capable of,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sion Col</hi> viſited <hi>p.</hi> 4.</note> unleſſe they will call a regular, full, and through obſervation of it, a testimony to it, the beſt part of this teſtimony conſiſting in going before one another, in a reall, not a verball refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You anſwer your ſelf,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> You ſay a reall reformation is the beſt teſtimony to the covenant; True, And therefore (ſay I) not the only teſtimony.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Doth a reall obſervation of the covenant hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a verball teſtimony to it, nay doth it not enforce it; I might deſervedly queſtion my reality for God and his cauſe, If I would not expreſſe that reality in words upon occaſion given.</p>
            <p>'Tis poſſible indeed for the verball profeſſion to be without the reall but not poſſible for the reall to be without the verball; but you ſay the covenant is not capable of a verball teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to it; Alas poor Covenant! It ſeems thou maiſt be well thought of, but not well ſpoken off? Thou maiſt be capable of a verball oppoſition and deniall, as of being called an <hi>old almanack out of date,</hi> but not of a verball appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation. Thy wound is broader (it ſeems) then thy plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
            <p>But Thirdly, How is it that you plead ſo much for the reall obſervation of the Covenant? I fear, not to further the reall, but to hinder the verbal; I diſlike your p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115038:9"/>of zeal for a reall reformation; you plead for it only to get the greater advantage againſt it; your heat of zeal for the covenant is like that of ſome herbs, hot in the mouth cold in the ſtomack.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To inrich their title, they add,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſited p. 4.</note> As alſo againſt the errours and hereſies,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Tell not the Miniſters of loving rich titles,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> either for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves or their books, your boaſting of your ſelves is as ridiculous as nauſecus; I pray who are they that aſſume to themſelves or have be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owed upon them, theſe titles in print, <hi>The richly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nointed, A Preacher to the two greateſt Congregations in England; A heart the beſt headed, and a head the beſt hearted of all the ſons of men: A man that hath the gifts and graces of ten thouſand rare men met in one? Men who look upon the word of Christ as impartially as men made of fleſh and bloud are like to do in any juncture of time that may fall out.</hi> Are not theſe ſwelling words? theſe are enriched titles;
<note place="margin">Mat. 21.28. Phil. 2.3.</note> doth this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the ſpirit of Chriſt and his Goſpel? he was <hi>lowly in heart,</hi> and bids each to eſteem other <hi>better then themſelves?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But they add againſt errours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They had need, for you are daily adding to errours. But this touching of errours, is the touching the apple of your eye, and the gainfull occupation of your ſilver ſhrines; 'Tis obſerveable that all along in your book, you give not the Reader the leaſt intimation of a diſlike of any particular errour (though never ſo damnable) mentioned in all the Catalogue. Only in your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> age you tell the world, that errouts are a great grief to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> heart, and that you oppoſe them in your Miniſtery ('tis a good to beleeve it, as to go where 'tis done) you dare not come neer an expreſſion of diſlike to errours by twelve ſcore, and now the Miniſters expreſſe their zeal againſt them; how doth your render nature make you weep for <hi>Tammuz?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But there is no further matter if conſequence in theſe words, againſt the errours, hereſies,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. <hi>p.</hi> 4.</note> and blasphemies of the times,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>then in the foregoing words, A teſtimony to the truth of Jeſus Christ, Therefore theſe paſſages are broadly Tauto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To rectifie you; The Miniſters in teſtifying <hi>for the truth,</hi> &amp;c.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:115038:10"/>owned the <hi>Confeſſion of faith,</hi> and the doctrines of truth he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d forth in the Scripture; and in ſaying againſt the errours, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they diſclaim and diſcover the things that are oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite unto them; they have not the Sectarian art to be friends to truth, and to be ſilent when errours that deſtroy truth are broa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched; to look toward heaven and earth at the ſame inſtant. The two fore-mentioned branches are therefore as far from being Tautologicall, as you from being either <hi>Logicall,</hi> or <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicall.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſited <hi>p.</hi> 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hereſies are imperiouſly ſentenced, as if the chair of</hi> Papal <hi>Infallibility, were tranſlated from Rome to</hi> Sion Colledge.</p>
            <p>Name one of thoſe errours in the Catalogue which the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (and that writing we cannot as yet deny to be the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of religion) condemns not:
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> if ſo, 'tis not <hi>Ex imperio</hi> but <hi>Ex officio</hi> to diſcover them, and for your ſcoff of the <hi>Chair of Papal infallibility,</hi> know that the Miniſters are as far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the chair <hi>of infallibility,</hi> as for the Chair in Swan-Alley.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the next impreſſion mollifie your title,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>p.</hi> 5.</note> ſay not against er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and hereſies, but uſe this Chriſtian and ſoft explication (as we account and call them errours and hereſies).</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tender-hearted Sir,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> Spare your counſell, or if you will give it, expect no fee, had ever Miniſters or Chriſtians ſuch adviſe given them before? <hi>Peter</hi> was called <hi>Satan</hi> for bidding Chriſt to pity himſelf, but what would <hi>Chriſt</hi> have called him, had <hi>Peter</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired Chriſt to have pitied <hi>Satan?</hi> The hereticall devil muſt not be uſed gently, 'Tis a cruell kindeneſſe to truth to do ſo; <hi>Diabolus non eſt leniter palpandus</hi> (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) when you had to do with M <hi>Edwards</hi> (of bleſſed memory) then 'twas <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">Pereat Pap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, pereantimp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mageſtrat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aut im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n dogma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treni pereat to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; ſalve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur Deo ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gloria ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> verbu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleſia, ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> cul. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> with you, rebuke them cuttingly, but when we have to do with hereſies it muſt be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, gently, muſt it? yes, uſe mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifying expreſſions (I pray deal gently with hereſies for <hi>I.G.</hi> his ſake) but hereſies have more need of <hi>Coraſives</hi> then lenitives, of iron then of oyle (was <hi>Auguſtine</hi> called <hi>Malleus Haereticorum</hi> for uſing mollifying expreſſions?) had you given us the advice of <hi>Luther,</hi> we would have thankt you. <hi>Let the pope periſh, ungodly Magiſtrates, The Patrons of ungodly opinions, of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, let all the world periſh, only let not the glory of God periſh,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115038:10"/>his Church, his Worſhip. But why speak we of</hi> Luthers <hi>ſpirit? your</hi> advice is more unſutable to the ſpirit of the Scripture. <hi>Rebuke them ſharply</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>that they may be ſound in the faith. Earneſtly contend for the faith. Damnable hereſies. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate concerning the faith, filthy dreamers, Curſed children, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly men, bruit beaſts, Clouds without water,</hi> Tit. 1.13. Jude. 3.4.12. 2 Pet. 2.1. 2 Tim. 3 8. Jude, 8. 2 Pet. 2.14. 2 Pet. 2.12. <hi>&amp;c,</hi> And yet forſooth, we muſt be all for ſoftneſſe and molliſying. The Lord pardon our ſinfull ſoftneſſe formerly. The time paſt may ſuffice to have connived at you: Shall you be bolder to ſin then we to ſpeak? God forbid.</p>
            <p>But wherein muſt the Miniſters expreſſe their ſoftneſſe? he tels us, for he gives us direction, as well as exhortation, though he is more wicked in preſcribing the manner of doing, then the thing to be done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Say not a teſtimony againſt Errours and Hereſies, but ſay, as we account and call Errours and Hereſies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His plain meaning is, Be doubtful whether thoſe damnable Errours and Hereſies be ſuch or no: Be <hi>Scepticks, Seekers, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectants, Dubitants,</hi> never beleeve any thing. When men deny the Scriptures to be the <hi>foundation of faith,</hi> ſay, This is an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, as we think: when men deny the Divinity of the Son and holy Ghoſt, ſay, Theſe are hereſies (as we conceive) when hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and hell are denied, ſay this is an hereſie, as we account, and ſo of the reſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Non eſt hoc Chriſtiani pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctari aſſ rtioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Tolle aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones &amp; Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianiſmum tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſti Sanctu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Spiritas non eſt. ſcepticus, nec o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piniones in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us noſtris, ſed aſſertiones. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pſâ vitâ &amp; omni experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d certiores produc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t.</hi> Luth.</note> Though the Lord hath not with-held you from giving, yet for his Chriſts ſake, he keep us from taking this advice; We who teach others to beleeve, ſhall we beleeve nothing our ſelves? if we may not be ſo certain as to write againſt errours, how ſhould we be ſo certain as to die in opppſition to errours? Should one lay down his life for he knows not what? Did thoſe bleſſed Martyrs in Queen <hi>Maries daies</hi> ſay, That <hi>Tranſubstanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> was an errour, as they thought? Beſides, are there any things in the world ſo certain as the matters of faith? The Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.2. <hi>of a fulneſſe of aſſurance of underſtanding,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Famous is that ſpeech of <hi>Luther</hi> which in the margin I give you in his own words, <hi>Non eſt hoc Christiani pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toris non delectari aſſertionibus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>It ſavours not of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, when men are not delighted with poſitive aſſertions, Take
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115038:11"/>away aſſertions, and thou haſt taken away Chriſtianity. The holy Ghoſt is no Sceptick, nor doth in produce opinions in our hearts, but certain aſſertions more ſure then life it ſelf, and all experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> &amp;c. Certainly if I may know any thing to be a truth, I may and muſt upon that ground know the contrary to be an errour; as if I know that this is a truth, That <hi>Christ</hi> is God, I certainly know that this is an errour, to ſay, He is not God; and therefore by your putting us to beleeve nothing for an errour, you will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain us to beleeve nothing for a truth. And if this be ſo, to what end ſerves preaching? Do Miniſters preach, and people hear fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles or truths? Further, if nothing be to be certainly known, for an errour, with what zeal can <hi>any way</hi> by you be oppoſed, when as you are and muſt be uncertain, whether you ſtrike a friend or a foe, a truth or an errour? And if ſo, How can you declaim againſt the way of <hi>Preſbytery?</hi> for ought you know it may be a truth, How or why againſt the reſtraint of <hi>herecicks,</hi> deniall of <hi>liberty of conſcience?</hi> And where are you then, Sir? But are you ſo undoubted, and certain, and poſitive, as you ſeem to your ſelf to be, when you oppoſe the truth? and muſt we be purely <hi>doubtfull,</hi> when we are oppoſing of <hi>errours?</hi> Did not you bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemouſly deny the Scripture to be the <hi>foundation</hi> of faith, with that aſtoniſhing expreſſion going before it, <hi>[Queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe]</hi> no writing whatſoever is the <hi>foundation of Chriſtian Religion?</hi> Though in this laſt Pamphlet your own conference (I hope) would not ſuffer you to put it in. Muſt you ſay que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionleſſe for errours, and muſt we come with an (as we think) againſt errours?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You extend your title againſt a toleration of errours alſo.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſited <hi>p.</hi> 5.</note> Now a toleration is a meer</hi> non ens, <hi>a thing not in being, and therefore you teſtify againſt that of which God made the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If a toleration be not no thank to you,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> I am confident 'tis your darling endeavour to effect it; You ſay, that becauſe a toleration is nothing, to ſpeak againſt it, is to ſpeak againſt that which Gud made the world of; Prophanely enough! But ſure you meant not to compare a toleration to the nothing of which God made the world, but to the <hi>Chaos</hi> out of which God made the worid: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f God made the world of it, I am ſure you have mar'd the world by it. But 'tis ſo far from being that of which God made the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115038:11"/>world, that it is rather that for which God may deſtroy the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If I had a captious pen, there would be no difficulty to finde a calumniating inſinuation againſt the Parliament.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>p</hi> 5. <hi>Anſ.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>For the calcumniating inſinuation againſt the Parliament, where lies it? turn not Sycophant, but give me leave to ſhew you your calumniating inſinuation againſt the Parliament: for this teſtimony of the Miniſters hath been in many a wiſe Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament mans hand; and for you (a mean man in compariſon) to dare to finde out a calumniation againſt them, which they could never finde out againſt themſelves, what is this but for you to prefer your ſufficiency to theirs, and to ſhew that they cannot couſult, without your aſſiſtance? But if there be a toleration, if doth not follow the Parliament is to be blamed; perhaps 'tis a toleration not <hi>given,</hi> but <hi>taken.</hi> 'Tis not from Parliamentary <hi>licenſe,</hi> but Sectaries their <hi>licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This preſent generation is fairly acquitted from being the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours of theſe errours,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſited <hi>p.</hi> 6.</note> becauſe theſe errours are ſaid in the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony to be the ſpawn of old, accurſed hereſies; dead and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried long ago, and now by ſeducers revived. Now revivers are no authours<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I am confident the Sectaries of theſe times will give you but little thanks for taking from them the honour of being the authours of the mentioned errours;
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> their greateſt contention being, whoſe invention ſhould be moſt reputed for, and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of the ſaid errours. And whereas you ſay, That revivers of errours are no authours; the Sectaries again are little beholding to you; for the reviver of an errour is worſe, and more inexcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable then the authour, in as much as the reviver of a buried and a condemned errour, ſins againſt the preſident of the concurrent judgements of holy men in former ages, whereas the authour wanted the help of former guides; I may truly ſay, that <hi>John Goodwin,</hi> ſins more inexcuſably, then <hi>Pelagius</hi> (whoſe ſoul ſeems by a ſtrange <hi>metempſuchoſis,</hi> to be tranſmigrated into M. <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win;</hi> ſave only that it meeting with <hi>Arminius</hi> by the way, ſifred into him all the flour of wit, and brought nothing, but the bran of hereſie to M. <hi>Goodwin</hi>) becauſe M. <hi>Goodwin</hi> though he be not
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115038:12"/>guilty of the invention of the errours, yet of the publication and propagation of them againſt the counſels and writings of all the Orthodox ſince <hi>Pelagius</hi> his time. For your acquitting therefore of this generation, you go too far, though you are an advocate to plead for errours, yet you muſt not be a judge to <hi>acquit</hi> them, and to acquit a whole generation at one clap, is with the moſt; the ſea of your charity gaineth ſo much toward heretikes, that its quite dried up toward the Orthodox. You are ſuch a prodigall of charity toward the one, that when you ſhould contribute to the other, you will be found a beggar. But take heed, leaſt if you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit this <hi>generation from hereſie,</hi> the next generation condemn your ſelf for hereſie. <hi>Judicium melius poſteritatis erit.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>The age to come,</l>
               <l>May paſſe your doom.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>There are ſeverall Miniſters of Chriſt to my knowledge in the Province of London (no Independents) commenſurable for worth with the talleſt Subſcribers,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſited <hi>p.</hi> 6.</note> though not to ſome of them in Church livings, by two or three, for whom God provided ſome bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thing then to ſuffer them to fall into the ſnare of ſo unworthy a ſubſcription.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſaid even now,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> they were only reputed the <hi>Miniſters of Chriſt,</hi> for want of mens knowing better, and now you ſay, They are the Miniſters of Chriſt to your knowledge; you want a better <hi>memory for ſo little honeſty.</hi> You add, That theſe Miniſters have not ſubſcribed the Teſtimony: but now you ſee many of their names ſubſcribed in this laſt Edition of the Teſtimony, Will you ſay, they are Miniſters? You finde that they love not to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graced with the praiſes of your pen for abſtaining.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You ſay that the ſubſcribers exceed the reſt in two or three Church livings.</hi> Theſe are exceeding daies only for Sectaries, The Orthodox have but ſhort commons<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they are rich in imploiments and poor in paiments. You are quite contrary, you are paid for being a hearer of your people, but it were well with the Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox, if they were paid for preaching to their people. You are the Preachers under worldly glory, The Orthodox are under the cro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, however I deſire to be as far from envy at your condition, as imitation of your own opinions; Your gains would be my joy, were not religion the looſer.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:115038:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>You ſcraple together a few ſaying or paſſages out of ſeverall mens books, whereof ſome are fair truths,</hi> &amp;c.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. <hi>p.</hi> 7. <hi>Anſw,</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>For the fairneſſe of your truths, ther's not one of them, but hath a face of ſoot, and of a blackmore, but I beleeve they are accounted fair in their own Countrey, in <hi>Errour-alley,</hi> but in an orthodox region they are very deformed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To reproach mens opinions without anſwering any one reaſon or ground upon which they build their aſſertions,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. <hi>p.</hi> 7.</note> is the Way for propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is not one mentioned errour in all the Catalogue,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> but is its own <hi>reproach,</hi> and its own <hi>refutation:</hi> And the frequency of your being braid in the morter of an anſwer, hath made hitherto but little of your folly to depart from you. A confutation would adde too much reputation to the errours. Beſides, when Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſee that their errours deſerve diſputation, they thereby think, that they deſerve eſtimation; 'tis their cuſtome to turn truths in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to controverſies, and controverſies into truths. And at all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations you ſtill go away with the victory, but eſpecially, when you are able to ſay nothing. The <hi>preſent work</hi> of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, was <hi>diſcovery:</hi> Refutation, if judg'd convenient may fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You rend a parcel of words out of the body of a large diſcourſe,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. p. 8. <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                  </note> which may carry ſome face of an unſound ſaying.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſeems your fair truths, of which you even now ſpake, have but a foul face; ſurely the beſt part of all your errours, is the face; if <hi>Satan</hi> intended to limn any part well, it would be that; and for the rending the parcel of words out of the body of the diſcourſe; If you have a deſire that the whole body ſhould be ſeen; the Reader is in the margin referr'd to it, and yet if any parcel of a paſſage ſeem'd to make for you, the Subſcribers ſet down that too, but indeed commonly the whole paſſage was a wrapt complication of errours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You ſhew not in what part of their ſayings the errour lies.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. <hi>p.</hi> 8. <hi>Anſw.</hi> There's <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. p. 9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Shew you in what part of any ſaying almoſt the errour doth not lie; commonly the diſeaſe is epidemicall over the whole paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The night is too far ſpent for them to think, that men will judge er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour or truth by their magiſterial votes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:115038:13"/>
            <p>Why make you not a right uſe of this departure of the <hi>night?</hi> Is it not a ſhame to hold ſuch ungodly opinions in the day of the Goſpel-light? They that are drunk with hereſie, are drunk even in the <hi>day.</hi> T' was bad to be ſo in the <hi>night of Popery;</hi> 'tis abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, in <hi>the day of Reformation;</hi> what a brazen brow hath hereſie to out-look the light of the Scripture, nay to put it out. Oh that I could hear more of you ſay <hi>to your errours</hi> (as <hi>the angel to Jacob</hi>) <hi>let me goe from you for the day appeareth</hi> Well, take heed, if you ſtill goe on to commit night ſins in the day time, leſt you ſhorten <hi>Englands day of grace,</hi> and <hi>haſten her night of Woe;</hi> If ever a <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> threatned ſuch a <hi>night,</hi> heretiques do: I aſſure you, Sir, <hi>Your new light hath in a manner put out your old heat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For your ſaying, That the night is too far ſpent to judge errours by the votes of Miniſters. We bleſſe God that the night is ſo far ſpent, as that we ſee how to judge your errours by the light of the Scriptures; a light that you would fain eclipſe, for fear of diſcovery; a light, which if you loved, you would abominate theſe errours of darkneſſe; love the Scriptures, and hate the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, if <hi>you dare, if you can.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Men have put away thoſe childiſh things,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sion Coll.</hi> viſit. <hi>pag</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                  </note> to beleeve as the Church beleeves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And in ſtead thereof Sectaries put it away as a child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh thing, to beleeve as the word beleeves;</hi> you have made a fair change.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is not ſo much as any one ſyllable in the Covenant that enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth any man to the Preſbyteriall Government.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſit. <hi>p.</hi> 10. <hi>Anſw.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>But are there not many ſyllables in the Covenant, that engage, 1. To a Government. 2. To a Government according to the word of God.</p>
            <p>If to a Government, What will then become of <hi>Independency?</hi> which any further then it ſhapes it ſelf to <hi>Preſbytery</hi> is the very negation of Government, and as uſed by you, ſtands upon no other leg then a neceſſary violation of the Covenant, by a Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all errours, hereſies, and ungodly opinions in the world.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If the <hi>Covenant</hi> engageth to a <hi>Government</hi> according to the word of God, and the example, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> tremble to quetch againſt <hi>Preſbytery,</hi> the moſt agreeable <hi>Government</hi> to the Word, and if it be not ſo, Anſwer the many learned and pious Tractates,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115038:13"/>that have been put out for it, both by <hi>Scots</hi> and <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Anſwer the learned labour of the Aſſembly, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Ruther ſurds,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Gillespies</hi> books, and the book entituled, <hi>Jus divinum Regiminis Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> but you have a compendious way of Confutation, you blow away whole books with the dictates of three or four lines.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Was it in the integrity of your hearts,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſit. <hi>p.</hi> 11.</note> to diſcharge your duty conſcientiouſly, that you charge him with errours againſt the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Authority of the Scripture, who hath bent himſelf with the u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>termoſt of his end<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>avours for the vindication of their Divine Authority, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ho hath laboured in this argument as much, and with as much faithfulnes as any of you all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Was it from the <hi>lowlineſſe</hi> of your heart,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> that you prefer your ſelf before the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> learned and pious of the <hi>Subſcribers?</hi> Or was it from <hi>the logick of your head,</hi> that you form ſuch a child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh argument, <hi>viz.</hi> You may not be taxed with errours about the Authority of the Scriptures, becauſe you have written in <hi>vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of them?</hi> Did not <hi>Faustus Rhegienſis</hi> write a Treatiſe,
<note place="margin">Baron, Annal. <hi>Ton.</hi> 6 <hi>an.</hi> 490. <hi>Sect.</hi> 31. <hi>Vid. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>id Hiſpal. de Script. eccl. cap.</hi> 14. <hi>Sune Scriptura Prophetica &amp; Apoſtolica, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t verbum De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipienda? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quaeſtionem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignam alioqui qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tractetur a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud theolo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>os Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>anos, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perit nobis hoc tempore Swenk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feldij deliratie,</hi> &amp;c <hi>De verbe Dei, l.</hi> 1 <hi>c</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>De gratiâ &amp; libero arbitrio,</hi> againſt the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> and yet, <hi>Dum captioſè videri vellet pugnare contra Pelagianos, compertus ſuit 'Pelagio favens, &amp; novus dogmatiſta.</hi> It matters not what men ſay, that themſelves doe, but what others that are wiſe and holy men, ſee that they doe; May not <hi>Bellarmine</hi> be charged with errours, about the Authority of the Scriptures, that hath la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beured in the juſtifying of their Divine Authority againſt the <hi>Schwenckfeldians</hi> with incomparable more ſinews and ſtrength, than you have ever done in your way? When did your pen ever, as his did, drop ſuch a paſſage as this, that the very queſtion, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Propheticall and Apostolicall writing is to be received as the Word of God, is unworthy to be handled by any Chriſtian divine, had it not been made neceſſary by the deliration of Swenck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feldius, and the Anabaptiſts denying it?</hi> Whereas your work is to preach and write againſt all Propheticall and Apoſtolicall writings, whether Originals or Tranſlations. Remember with what conſident heat you roſe up for the moſt horrid heretikes, <hi>Antiſeripturiſts and Antitrinitarians,</hi> &amp;c. In your <hi>Hagiomaſtix,</hi> and then conſider whether your ſaying that you bear the errours of the times, as a burden upon your ſoul, is to be beleeved; muſt this your ſaying, that errours are your burden, excuſe you from
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115038:14"/>erroneouſnes, when you ſay, that this opinion, that <hi>God is not one in three perſons, is not contrary to any manifeſt word of God;</hi> and this you ſay (in that place) that your opponents neither have proved,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hag.</hi> p. 35.</note> nor can prove; Though you ſay that errours are your burden, muſt you not be blamed for ſaying, <hi>That you know holy and heavenly Chriſtians,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hag.</hi> p. 36.</note> who deny that God is one in three perſons.</hi> Muſt your own titles and pretences upon, or in any book exempt you from a Charge, when as the matter couched under them condemns you? Nay, ought you <hi>not to be the more bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for your cloaked impiety;</hi> and for your reall enmity to the Scriptures under appearances and ſeeming friendſhip, <hi>Tuta fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> via—</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doe I not plainly,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sion Col</hi> viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>p.</hi> 11.</note> clearly, and diſtinctly enough declare unto the world in my Treatiſe concerning the Divine Authority of the Scripture; In what ſenſe I hold the Scriptures, whether Tranſlations or Originals to be the word of God, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the foundation of Chriſtian Religion;</hi> and in what not? <hi>Let the</hi> 13 <hi>and</hi> 15. <hi>pages of my ſaid book be lookt upon.</hi> Therefore you complain that the Subſcribers barely cite theſe words from your pen <hi>[Queſtionleſſe no writing whatſoever, whether Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or Originals, are the foundation of Christian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion]</hi> without citing thoſe other words of yours, <hi>pag.</hi> 13. wherein in a true ſenſe you aſſert them to be the Word of God.</p>
            <p>Your ſelf is the firſt man that ever I heard to commend you for clearneſſe,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> plainneſſe and diſtinctneſſe, your writings, throughout have more of words then matter, and yet more of mud then either. But</p>
            <p>At your command, I ſhall conſult the pages, wherein you would be thought to ſay, The Scriptures are the Word of God. In the former, as alſo <hi>pag.</hi> 17. where you ſeem to be moſt full in declaring your ſenſe, You ſay to this purpoſe; That you grant the matter and ſubſtance of the Scripture, <hi>The gracious counſels,</hi> to be the Word of God, as, <hi>That Chriſt is God and man, that he died, that he roſe again,</hi> &amp;c. (You are come to a high pitch of ingenuity, I aſſure you.) Theſe things you having ſaid, you thinke you may lawfully charge the Miniſters with craft and wickedneſſe, for ſetting down barely that concluſion of yours,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115038:14"/>
               <hi>pag.</hi> 18. <hi>Queſtionles no writing whatſoever, whether Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or Originals, are the foundation of Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. But what will pleaſe you? The Subſcribers are in ſome ſtrait how to content you, when they only ſet down the concluſion and reſult of your words, you ſay they deal wickedly, becauſe they expreſſe no more, and when they cite a whole page, you ſay, they doe it, that they may repreſent you to the Reader for a man of <hi>monſtrous and prodigious errours, one of which cannot be expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or contained in fewer words then would fill a whole page:</hi> Yet on the other ſide, If they pitch only upon the errour, you ſay, they cite your words barely, and ſuppreſſe <hi>craftily your ſenſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Though <hi>the</hi> Subſcribers did ſet down this your Concluſion without reciting your long-winded paſſages, which you premiſe, yet deſerve they not this your reviling,
<note place="margin">Div. author. of Scrip <hi>p.</hi> 18.</note> as if they had wrong'd you: For the concluſion being the reſult of the premiſſes, if your concluſion be crazie and hereticall, your premiſes muſt needs be ſo too, and therefore the ſetting of them down would not have helped you at all: and if the concluſion be not hereticall, why doe you not defend it againſt the accuſation of the Subſcribers, which you neither doe, nor dare to doe, but only ſend the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribers to the thirteenth page, leaving the poor eighteenth to mercie.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Suppoſe you had in the thirteenth page written the truth, therefore ought you not to be blamed for writing errours in the eighteenth page? Nay, ought you not the rather to be blamed? Suppoſe that <hi>found truths</hi> were laid on the top of your book, might you not be blamed for laying rotten errours at the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome: Satan knows that the one muſt make the other vendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and the Subſcribers did but labour herein to ſpoil his <hi>mercat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. I ſuppoſe the ſubſcribers did not ſet down your ſenſe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the divine Authority of the Scriptures in the thirteenth page, becauſe it had no relation either clear or doubtfull to the paſſage in this eighteenth page. For in the thirteenth page you ſay you aſſert the Scriptures to be the word of God; and here in the eighteenth page, you come with your Queſtionleſſe no writing whatſoever, whether tranſlations or originalls are the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:115038:15"/>
            <p>But you ſeem to complain that you who have granted the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>i.e.</hi> the gracious counſels, matter, ſubſtance of them to be the word of God, ſhould be blamed though you ſay <hi>Queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe no writing whatſoever is the foundation of Chriſtian religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> but miſtake not, for though you have granted what no Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, nay, what no chriſtian (in a ſenſe) did ever yet deny, yet upon what ground have you granted even this, you give the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der nothing to ſhew for this grant but only <hi>your good nature and ingenuity:</hi> you tell me <hi>pag.</hi> 13. that you beleeve the precious counſells, matter and ſubſtance of the Scripture to be of <hi>divine authority,</hi> but though you beleeve ſo, yet what ground give you <hi>me</hi> to beleeve ſo with you? none I am ſure p. 10. Div. Autho. where you deny <hi>both the Engliſh Scriptures and the Hebrew and Greek Originals themſelves to be the word of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Div. Autho. p. 10.</note> Nor give you me any ground to beleeve with you that the counſells of the ſcriptures are the word of God, in p. 12. when you ſay, <hi>That they who have the greateſt inſight into the originall languages, yea and who beleeve the Scriptures unto ſalvation;
<note place="margin">Div. Autho. p. 12.</note> cannot upon any ſufficient ground beleeve, any originall copie under heaven whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Hebrew or greek to be the word of God, with a world of ſuch stuff;</hi> Nor give you any ground to beleeve the matter, counſells &amp;c. of the Scripture to be the word of God, p. 18. where you ſay, <hi>Queſtionleſſe no writing whatſoever whether tranſlations or originalls are the foundation of Chriſtian</hi> religion, much leſſe in that of <hi>Hag.</hi> p. 38. where in regard of the <hi>mortality of words,</hi> you make the meaning of the originalls impoſſible to be certainly underſtood; nay by all theſe paſſages of yours you hinder me from beleving (as much as in you lieth) that the matter, <hi>ſubſtance, counſells,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>of the Scriptures are the word of God,</hi> for how can any beleeve <hi>the matter, ſubſtance</hi> &amp;c. of the Scripture to be the word of God, when as he muſt be <hi>uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> whether the written word or Scriptures wherein that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is contained are the word of God or no? I ſuppoſe when you ſay that the matter of the Scriptures, repreſented in tranſlations <hi>and originals</hi> is the word of God p. 17. you ſuppoſe that it ſhould be beleeved for ſuch; but upon what ground ought I to beleeve it? I hope you will not ſay becauſe a province of <hi>London-Miniſters</hi> ſaith it is to be beleeved, nor barely becauſe <hi>the ſpirit</hi> tels me is to be
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115038:15"/>believed for the word of God,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1 19.</note> for the ſpirit ſends me to the <hi>writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten word,</hi> and bids me by that to trie the ſpirits, and tells me I muſt beleeve nothing to be from God, or for my own eternall good, but what I finde <hi>written;</hi> I therefore deſire to go to the <hi>written word</hi> as <hi>reveal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d by God,</hi> for the building my confidence upon the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells and matter of the Scriptures (as pardon through Chriſt. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) But then <hi>J. Goodwin</hi> tels me this <hi>written word is not Gods word,</hi> nor are any writings in the world <hi>Originals or Tranſlations,</hi> to be lookt upon as ſuch; If ſo, they muſt be the word of vain man, and ſo I have no more to ſhew for the precious truths, that Chriſt died for ſinners and loſt man <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then mans word; I pray con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, what are become of your diſciples (to uſe your own phraſe) their ſoul proviſions, their hope of eternall bleſſedneſſe, when as thus you deny the written word? How doth my ſoul pitty your poor deluded followers who have ſuch a ſoul ſtarving or ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poyſoning ſhepheard ſet over them, the Lord knows I hardly write theſe things with dry eyes. Whereas therefore you ſend the ſubſcribers and readers to your pages alledged, I ſhall do the like, and deſire them to take notice that you make no diſtinction between the <hi>res credenda,</hi> and the <hi>ratio credendi,</hi> the matter to be beleeved, and the ground of beleeving that thing, <hi>the objectum materiale &amp; formale fidei;</hi> the matters to be beleeved, are thoſe precious truths of God, which you name p. 13. and ſuch like. the ground of beleeving them is the revelation of God in his writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten word Nor can any one beleeve thoſe truths with a divine faith as the truths of God,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoc verbum quod multis vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cib is multiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> mod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>olim De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us proſerre vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, viſum eſt ei lem literis &amp; libris ad Ecclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie ſuae uſum conſignare, un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; codem ſem. per manente verbo etſi non uno modo tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dito,</hi> Riv. Cat. Oath. Par. 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> unleſſe he firſt beleevs that they are revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and made known by God: This Revelation of God hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies been the foundation of faith, and (as the Apoſtle,) <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.1. ſaith <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; God hath afforded this at divers times, after divers manners, to his Church ſometimes by a live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly voice, at other times by writing, the authority of the revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion being the ſame, the manner of revealing divers. * But now ſince the truths of God were expreſſed in writing, what is the grouad of your faith, but this <hi>it is, written,</hi> and if you deny the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of the words and ſay that they are not from divine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration,, you muſt of neceſſity alſo deny the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of the matter and hold that the matter which you ſay is only the word of God, is unworthy of a Chriſtians belief: I pray what courſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115038:16"/>took Chriſt and his Apoſtles to prove their doctrinall aſſertions,
<note place="margin">Mat 44.6.7.10 Mat. 1.2. Mar. 9.12. Mar. 11.17. Luk. 18.31.22.37. 24 44 46. Joh. 10.34. Act. 13.33. 15.85. Rom. 3.4. 10.81. 9.13. 11.26. 12 19. 14 11. 13.9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 1 Cor. 1.19. 1 Cor. 1.31. 1 Cor. 2.9. 9.9. 1 Cor 15.54. 2 Cor 9.9. Gal. 3.13. 4.22. Heb 10.7. 1 Pet. 11.6. Mar. 15.28. Act. 8.32.35. Rom. 9.17. 10.11. 11.2 Gal. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. 1 Tim. 5.18. 1 Pet. 2.6. Mat. 21.42. 26 56 Luk. 24.27.45. Act. 17.2 11. 18.28. Rom. 1.2. 16.26. 1 Cor. 15 3.</note> and the matters they taught, but by the Scriptures, and when they would render them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> fit for belief, they evermore tell how it is <hi>written.</hi> Conſult with the places in the margin, and you will finde that the matter, ſubſtance, precious counſells <hi>&amp;c.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Scriptures are proved to be <hi>credenda</hi> things to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved, becauſe they are written, deny then the written word (as you do <hi>in terminis</hi>) to be the word of God, and what formall object hath faith? poor faith without a written word! Yeeld your ſelf to that evident Scripture, <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.31. <hi>Theſe things are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten that yee might beleeve that Jeſus is the Chriſt the ſon of God, and that beleeving ye might have lift through his name:</hi> God makes theſe matters, <hi>Chriſt is the ſon of God;</hi> and <hi>life is to he had through his name,</hi> to be the objects and matter of my belief, but God makes the <hi>ratio</hi> or ground of my beleeving of theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to be their revelation by writing: See alſo <hi>Act.</hi> 14.24. <hi>Paul ſaith he beleeved all that was written in the Law and the prophets,</hi> So, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4. <hi>Things were written aforetime that through the patience and comfort of the Scriptures, we might have hope. So if you beleeve not Moſes writings, how ſhall you beleeve my words?</hi> Joh. 5.47.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Therefore doth not your ſending me only to the counſels, matter, ſubſtance of Tranſlations and Originals, as the Word of God, and your deniall that the written Word is ſuch clearly ſhew, That you ſend me not to that Word of God, which the Scripture every where ſpeaks of, but to ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Scripture uſing to call the written Word of God, the Scripture (and very often, though in a Tranſlation) The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.39. is to ſearch the Scriptures, and were not they the written Word, <hi>How readeſt thou?</hi> Luk. 10.26. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderstandeſt thou what thou readeſt.</hi> Act. 8.30. and what Scriptures were thoſe the Apoſtle calleth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> given by inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of God? meaneth the Apoſtle neither Originals nor tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation? or both rather?</p>
            <p>It were eaſy to ſhew how in this point of your deniall the Scriptures for the foundation, as faith and Scriptures oppoſe you, ſo likewiſe ſundry holy and learned writers that have had oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to touch upon the ſubject.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:115038:16"/>
            <p>Let theſe following (aſſerting the Scriptures for the word of God, and ſo the foundation of faith, and Chriſtian Religion) ſuffice for the vindication of the written word from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt you caſt upon it.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Quo plenius &amp; impreſſius tam ipſum, quam diſpoſitiones, &amp; voluntates adiremus, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentum adjecit litera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae, ſi quis velit de Deo inquirere, &amp; inquiſitum invenire, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vento <hi>credere,</hi> &amp; credito de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervire. <hi>Tertul. Apol.</hi> cap. 18.</note> 
               <hi>That we might go to God, his counſells, and will, more fully, and vigorouſly, he added the inſtrument of <hi>writing,</hi> if any would enquire of God, finde him, <hi>beleeve</hi> in him, and ſerve him.</hi> Tertullian.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Non per ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os ſalutis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrae diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem cogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vimus, quam per eos per quos Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium pervenit ad nos, quod quidem tunc praeconiave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt poſtea per Dei <hi>voluntatem</hi> in Scripturis nobis tradiderunt fundamentum &amp; columnam fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei noſtrae futu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um. <hi>Irenaeus. Adverſ. Hereſ</hi> lib. 3. cap. 1 <hi>vide</hi> lib. 3. c. 2.</note> 
               <hi>We know not Gods dispoſall (or ordering) of our ſalvation, but by thoſe, by whom the Gospel came to us, which they formerly preached, afterward by the counſell of God delivered to us in the <hi>Scriptures</hi> to be the foundation, and pillar of our faith,</hi> Irenaeus.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Singuli Sermones, ſyllabae, apices, puncta, in divinis Scripturis plena ſunt ſenſibus. <hi>Hier in cap.</hi> 1. <hi>ad</hi> Eph.</note> 
               <hi>The ſeverall speeches, ſyllables, tittles, points in the divine Scriptures, are full of ſenſe.</hi> Hier.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Perſuaſiſti mihi Domine Deus non eos qui crederent libros tuos, quos tantâ omnibus ſerè gentibus authoritate fundaſti, eſſe culpandos, ſed eos qui non crederent, nec audiendos eſſe ſi qui forte mihi dicerent unde ſcis illos libros unius veraciſſimi Dei ſpiritu, eſſe humano generi miniſtratos, id ipſum enim maximè credendum erat. <hi>Aug Conf</hi> lib. 6.</note> 
               <hi>O my Lord God, thou haſt perſwaded me, not that they who beleeved thy <hi>books,</hi> which thou haſt founded with ſo much autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, in almost all nations, were to be blamed, but thoſe who beleeved them not, and that thoſe were not to be heard, who might haply ſay to me, whence doſt thou know that thoſe <hi>books</hi> were administred to man-kinde by the Spirit of the only moſt true God? for this thing was <hi>chiefly</hi> to be <hi>beleeved.</hi>
               </hi> Auguſtine.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Chry. hom. 1. in <hi>Mat.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>If it be blame-worthy to ſtand in need of the writing of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and not to imbrace the grace of the spirit; how great a fault is it, after the enjoyment of ſo great an help, not to gain by it, but to deſpiſe the</hi> writings, <hi>as if they had been laid before us in vain, and thereby to draw upon our ſelves greater puniſhment.</hi> Chryſ.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:115038:17"/>
            <p>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Homin's qui intra Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae pomaeria ſunt, de ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate non quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, eſt enim p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>incipium. Quomodopoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt eſſe diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli Chriſti ſi doctrinam Chriſti velint in dubium vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care? quomodo verae Eccleſiae membra ſi de fundamento Eccleſiae dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare velint? Quomodo id ſibi probari petent quod ad probanda alia ſemper aſſumunt? <hi>Gerb. loc. Com. Tom</hi> 1. de S. ſer. p 7 Sect. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Men, that are within the</hi> pale <hi>of the Church, make no queſtion of the authority of the</hi> Scripture; <hi>for it is a</hi> principle. <hi>How can they be the Diſcioles of Chriſt if they will call the doctrine of Chriſt into question, how can they be members of the Church, if they will doubt of the foundation of the Church? How can they deſire to have that proved, which they make uſe of to prove all other things by?</hi> Gerhard.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="g" place="margin">In fidei controverſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s dijudicandis nec ab Hebraeis nec a Graecis pendere volunt Papiſtae, multiplicatis quaeſtiunculis quaeſivit Ieſuita omnem ſacrae ſcripturae fidem a judicio huma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſuſpendere &amp; de <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſcripturae qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> habemus dubitationem omnium mentibus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, ut his athe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mi radimentis hom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es a vert Dei cognitione abſtract<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s facilius Antichriſt dominationi ſubjiciant. <hi>Andr Rivet.</hi> Q 4. <hi>de ſcrip</hi> Tom. 1.</note> 
               <hi>In determining of controverſies of faith, the Papiſts (note this</hi> M. <hi>Goodwin) will not stand, either to the</hi> Hebrew <hi>or</hi> greek originals; <hi>and</hi> (Baily <hi>the Jeſuite) by multiplying queſtions hath ſought to make the belief of the holy Scripture to depend upon mans judgement and they caſt doubts into all mens mindes, about the authority of the</hi> holy Scriptures <hi>which we have; that by theſe rudiments of</hi> Atheiſm, <hi>they might ſubiect thoſe men to the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of</hi> Antichriſt, <hi>whom they have drawn from the knowledge of the true God.</hi> Andr. Rivet.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude with deſiring you in the fear of God to conſider whether that complaint which the learned <hi>Rivetus</hi> makes of <hi>Albertus Pighius</hi> ſute not too evidently with your ſelf; whom as <hi>Rivet</hi> ſaith, uttered ſuch blaſphemous expreſſions as theſe; <hi>explicent ſcripturarij
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Explicent ſcripturarij iſti unde nobis cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt haec eſſe Moyſi ſcripta que ſub ej<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine legimus &amp; ſi viderem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tos r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d deret M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>yſi tam multis ſeculis mortui, eſſe ſcriptama<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>? haec &amp; fimilia querebat a n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis</hi> proph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us iſte, <hi>quae quor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. nemo poteſt ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norare nifi qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> sponte vult de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Rivetus <hi>ubiſupra;</hi> and he ſaith that the Papiſts are herein worſe then the <hi>tradi. tores.</hi> who for fear delivered their Bibles to the Heathen to be burnt. <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſit. <hi>p.</hi> 12.</note> iſti</hi> &amp;c. let theſe that ſtand ſo much for the <hi>written word,</hi> tell us, how we can be certain that theſe are the writings of <hi>Moſes,</hi> which we read to go under his name, and how can they aſſure us that theſe things were written with <hi>Moſes</hi> his own hand who died ſo many years agoe? —He concludes with calling this <hi>Albertus Pighius</hi> a prophane fellow and ſaith, that he that ſeeth not whether theſe things tend is willing to deceive himſelf; I verely fear (and without any breach of charity) that theſe <hi>ſcripturarij</hi> eſpecially of the presbyterian judgement ſhall not finde that favour from <hi>Joha Goodwin</hi> that a Sectarian Antiſcripturiſt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115038:17"/>hath found in his <hi>Hagiomaſtix</hi> in which calendar he was highly Sainted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Was it in the integrity of your hearts, and to diſcharge your duty conſcienciouſly: that you muſt needs make it an errour or hereſie, to ſay that it were needleſſe for Satan to blinde the eyes of naturall men if they had not eyes to ſee, and to receive the glorious light of the Gospel, when it is declared unto them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But there you ſtop; you do not proceed to the next words, which have a moſt horrid aſpect, <hi>Men are not blinde for want of eyes, but for want of light, and when light, or truth is diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to them, they have faculties ſuitable, fit, and apt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it;</hi> But what kinde of blindeneſſe call you that, to be in the dark, and to have good eyes: 'tis a blindeneſſe that can neither in a ſpirituall or a naturall reſpect be cal'd a blindeneſſe, the blindeneſſe of a naturall man is ſuch, as argueth a periſhing of the power of <hi>ſpirituall ſeeing, or diſcerning</hi> (according to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>he cannot know the things of the Spirit of God.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2, 14) Converſion is the <hi>reſtoring of ſight,</hi> not of <hi>light</hi> only; the <hi>opening of the eyes,</hi> not the bringing of light to them who have eyes already. <hi>Act.</hi> 26.18. raiſing up, and <hi>putting life into a dead man,</hi> and not the <hi>unbinding,</hi> or the <hi>unfittering</hi> of a <hi>living.</hi> Epheſ. 2.</p>
            <p>The words, which you deny to be an errour viz. <hi>'Tis a need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe thing for Satan to blinde if they have not eyes to ſee,</hi> are very falſe, for notwithſtanding Satans making us blinde, we are blinde of our ſelves, according to Scripture, which ſaith that <hi>naturall men cannot know the things of the Spirit of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.14. and yet <hi>that the God of this world hath blinded them,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. when the Scripture ſaith, that <hi>a naturall man is carried captive by Satan,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.26. doth it therefore follow, he is not a ſlave to ſin becauſe to Satan? Satan may keep men in blindeneſſe, and ſlavery, and make men more to pleaſe themſelves in both, but its certain that we are both ſlaves to ſin, and blinde in ſin alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Where or in what clauſe or phraſe of this enſuing period,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sion Coll.</hi> viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. <hi>p.</hi> 12, 13.</note> lies the errour or hereſie—If God ſhould not make men capable of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving, I mean indue men with ſuch principles, abilities or gifts of reaſon, judgement, memory or underſtanding, by the diligent
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115038:18"/>improvement whereof they might come to be convinced of a readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and willingneſſe in God to receive them into favour, upon their repentance (<hi>upon which Conviction, true repentance and turning to God, ALLWAIES follows</hi>) they which are condemned would have their mouths opened againſt God and furniſhed with an excuſe. The Parentheſis I ſuppoſe is innocent. The conſequence, If God ſhould not make men capable</hi> &amp;c. <hi>is built upon this principle, that a plea for want of power for performance, is an excuſe in the caſe of non-performance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You have in the ſetting down of your <hi>innocent parentheſi,</hi> ſhewn your ſelf very nocent, and deceitfull; for, as if your conſcience had taken your former aſſertion ill at your hands, you left cut that word, <hi>ALLWAIES,</hi> in your late Pamphlet, which word the ſubſcribers charged you with in their teſtimony, and would clearly have carried the ſenſe thus, <hi>grace and converſion infallibly follow upon mans improvement of his naturall abilities,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, For your <hi>conſequence</hi> that <hi>if God ſhould not make men capeable of beleeving</hi> (upon that principle <hi>that a plea for want of power for per formance,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tum omnis res<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponſandi anſa praeciditur Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelitis, cum ſtatuitur poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam ſerendi fructus per gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam internam ipſis eſſe colla tam contra ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro tam diu ma net reſpan an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i materia, quam diu non ſtatui tur Iſraelita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> a Deo accepiſſe potentiam fruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſerendi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepeſſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>, ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> per grat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> internam u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>po tèquae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ertur Act. Synod.</hi> p. 92. <hi>Art</hi> 3.4.</note> is an excuſe in the caſe of non-perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance) they that are condemned would have their mouths opened againſt Gods proceedings, and be furniſhed with an excuſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let the reader take notice, that you in this as in that which follows lovingly joyn hands with the <hi>Arminians,</hi> the <hi>Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrants,</hi> who ſay thus: <hi>Then is the mouth of the Iſraelites ſtopped, when it is granted that they had power given them by the internall grace of God to bring forth fruit, but on the other ſide ſo long will the mouth be open, as it is not granted that the Iſraelites had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of God power to bring forth fruit, I ſay, had received it by internall grace, by which only it can be conferred;</hi> 'Tis plain you joyn with the erroneous; but you ask, where lieth the errour? I anſwer, I ſhall tell you where there lieth ſomething as bad, I mean blaſphemy. Your mouth (to be ſure) is <hi>widely opened</hi> againſt God, for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of this aſſertiom (<hi>If God ſhould not make men able to beleeve they might accuſe God</hi>) is but this, that God is unjuſt in commanding man in his fal'n eſtate to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the things which he hath voluntarily diſabled himſelf to perform; by which opinion you muſt needs make Gods <hi>ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty</hi> to be impaired with <hi>mans ability,</hi> and to be limited to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115038:18"/>mans <hi>ſinfully,</hi> and <hi>voluntarily</hi> contracted <hi>impotency;</hi> or if God will not ſuffer it ſo to be, the holy commands of God are by <hi>J.G.</hi> openly charged to be worthy of having our mouths wide open againſt them; Is not every man, as a man, a debtour to God, and a creature tied to obedience? and doth his <hi>making himſelf inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient</hi> to diſcharge the debt diſcharge him from payment? and it would follow, if ſuch impotency excuſed from duty, and from the obligation of the command, that thoſe men were moſt excuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that were moſt ſinfull, and had by long accuſtoming them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſin, made themſelves moſt unable to leave and forſake ſin; nay, if by reaſon hereof, God did not command obedience from them, it would follow, that ſuch did not ſin at all (for where there's no precept there's no tranſgreſſion) and ſo according to you, by a mans progreſſe in ſin, he ſhould make himſelf ceaſe to be ſinfull.</p>
            <p>Nor did <hi>Pelagius</hi> himſelf ever utter any ſentence more to the ſwelling of nature, or prejudice of grace, then your ſelf have uttered in your <hi>parentheſis,</hi> wherein you ſay that by the improvement of nature, a man may attain to ſuch a conviction as upon which ſaving converſion <hi>ALLW AIES</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows; what place is here left for grace? what agreement with the Apoſtle. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7 <hi>Who maketh thee to differ from another?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Epiſcopius.</note> (M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Goodwins</hi> anſwer; <hi>my ſelf by my improovement of nature made me to differ,</hi> would have fallen little ſhort of blaſphemie.) What agreement with Chriſt. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.24. <hi>Now they have both ſeen and hated</hi> (for all that) <hi>both me and my father;</hi> The principles of nature after the fall improved to the utmoſt, are ſo far from carrying a man to God, that they leave a <hi>man dead in ſin,</hi> and his very higheſt and moſt refined part, his <hi>carnall minde is enmity to God, Rom.</hi> 8 7. And again the Scripture teſtifieth that <hi>the world cannot receive the ſpirit of truth Ioh.</hi> 14 17. And Rom 5.6. <hi>Christ died for us being, as ungodly, ſo without strength;</hi> So Phil. 1.29. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto you it is given,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to beleeve;</hi> and Phil. 2.13. <hi>It is God that worketh in you both to will and to do, of his good pleaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your good friend M. <hi>Bucer</hi> you ſay is no <hi>Arminian,</hi> and I ſay he is far from being like you in this point, Hear him upon that of our Saviour, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12.39. <hi>Therefore they could not beleeve,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115038:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:115038:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:115038:20"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:115038:20"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:115038:21"/>
               <hi>What could be ſaid more fully and plainly</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>for the predeſtination of God that ordaineth all things, and againſt that which ſome aſcribe to free will,
<note place="margin">Quid patentius, &amp; apertius di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci poſſit, pro Dei omni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinantis prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinatione, &amp; contraid, quod quidam libero arbitrio trib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, nempe bo minem ex ſua virtute credere poſſe.</note> that a man may by his own im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement beleeve in Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. You go on.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You cite a whole page together, conſiſting of three, or four and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty lines under the name, and notion of one and the ſame errour</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The ſubſcribers have not (as yet) the art of pleaſing you; even now they cited your words too ſparingly, now too copiou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly; you are ever complaining; you will pardon them; ſo croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked a piece cannot eaſily be fitted; and it was the firſt time that ever you imployed them; you conjecture many reaſons why they ſhould cite your paſſage ſo fully, even to the filling of a whole ſide in <hi>quarto</hi> with 34. lines. but you meet not with the right reaſon among them all; It was briefly this, you have ſuch a long-winded ſtile, and ſuch a foggy <hi>conceptus,</hi> that you cannot write a ſlieght notion which may be couched in four lines, under <hi>thirty four lines,</hi> as in the forecited inſtance is plain, and that made the ſubſcribers, rather to condeſcend to your expreſſions, then to be indulgent to their own inclinations, Be quicker hereafter.</p>
            <p>But you complain of their want <hi>of conſcience in tranſcribing a whole page under the name of one errour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Are you angry becauſe they found but one Error in 34. lines? You have rather cauſe to praiſe their candor, then to blame their computation. Had they been as ſevere in reckoning your Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors as you are exact in numbring your lines, you would have ſpared this charge.</p>
            <p>The paſſage according to your arithmetick being 34. lines, I ſhall not here tranſcribe it; but the ſumme of it is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That if God ſhould deprive men of all power to beleeve, and yet ſhould perſwade them to beleeve, with that affection wherein he expreſſeth himſelf in the Scriptures, even to thoſe that periſh, this would be harder then injuſtice it ſelf; God would be like a King, that cauſeth a mans leggs to be cut off for a fault, and yet urge him to run a race with thoſe that have their limbs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Arminians</hi> were your Schoolmaſters, when you learned this leſſon;
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> The <hi>Remonstrants</hi> and you meet again.</p>
            <p>Their very words are theſe. <hi>If a man have lost his ability,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115038:21"/>becauſe God hath taken it away in his juſt judgement by a deſerved puniſhment, truly the man is made excuſable,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Si potentiam a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſit, quia cam ſubſtraxit Deus juſto judici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> per panam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectò ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uſabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis redditur ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo, ſi cum De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> astum deinde poſtulat abillo quem fic punivit. i.e. Impotentem ad actum praeſtandum per ſubſtractionem gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia reddidit actum illum non exerceat.</hi> Act, Syn. 3, 4 <hi>pag.</hi> 145. <hi>Et certè num De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> hominem in aeternanco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>demnationem abijecere poſſit,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Is qui cum homine ita agit, tyrannus ſaeviſſimo Phalaride immanior,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ibid. Pone oculis militem eſſe multatum,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ibid.</hi> pag. 108.</note> though he perform not the command; And they leave it to the conſciences of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines to judge, whether God can with juſtice caſt ſuch a man into eternall damnation. Nay he that ſo deals with him would be a cruel tyrant</hi> (ſay they.) <hi>If a Generall command a blinde ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, though one who hath loſt his eyes for ſome grievous offence, to stand centinell, and threaten him if he doe not,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>You appear not yet heart-ſmitten notwithſtanding your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view of this paſſage in the Teſtimony; but you ſay it is a truth of God: and ſince you doe ſo; you are put upon proving in the next.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That they who periſh have power to beleeve, and repent. The Scriptures deny it; when they ſay that the world cannot receive the ſpirit, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.17. men by nature are <hi>dead in treſpaſſes, and ſins,</hi> Eph. 2. Without ſtrength. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.6. <hi>God worketh in us to will, and to doe, our ſufficiencie is of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. If man hath not power, prove, that this impotencie is meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paenall, as inflicted by God, ſo involuntarily induced by man (for that is the nature of a puniſhment properly ſo called) the Scripture ſaith man <hi>hath found out many inventions,</hi> Eccleſ 7. and that all his <hi>imaginations are evil,</hi> Gen. 6.5. and <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. that <hi>all fleſh hath corrupted its way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Prove that God hath not puniſhed mans rebellion with this impotencie. What death is that which is threatned upon the eating of the <hi>forbidden fruit, Gen.</hi> 2.17. and how extenſive is it?</p>
            <p n="4">4. That upon theſe praemiſſes it would be injuſtice and diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation in God, to command men to beleeve. Untill theſe things are proved, know that the large tranſcription of 34. lines, is from the crown of the head to the ſole of the foot all rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenneſſe.</p>
            <p>Sir, Your friend, and (as you pretend) your patron, <hi>Martin Bucer,</hi> ſalutes you in theſe words. <hi>They that for the aſſerting of the juſtice of God, before the tribunall of their own reaſon,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115038:22"/>fly to this,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qui his moti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tat Dei juſtitian aſſerant apud <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>unal ratio nis ſue, illò con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fugiunt, ut di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant aliquid vir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>um nobis ſupereſſe, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas vocati ado nino &amp; gratil ej<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> aljuti, ad rectam vitam pervenire p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſumus, ſi non ultro averti nos ab illâ patiamur: praeterquam, quod boc commento, rationi minimè ſatisfaciunt; eò praeterea adducunt ſe, ut ſi tueri iſtud ſuum commentum velint, neceſſariò negent Deum eſſe.</hi> Bucerus. <hi>in</hi> Rom. 9.</note> that they ſay we have ſome ſtrength left, by which being called by God, and aſſiſted by his grace we may come to a righteous life, beſides, that they ſatisfie not reaſon by this fiction of theirs, they alſo bring themſelves upon this strait, that if they will defend their fiction, they must <hi>deny there is a God;</hi>
               </hi> Though <hi>Bucer</hi> be in your books now he is dead, yet you would have been far from being in his, had he been living.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You ſay that this doctrine is moſt aſſuredly aſſerted by</hi> Paul <hi>and</hi> Peter;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sion Coll.</hi> vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it. <hi>pag</hi> 15.</note> 
               <hi>viz. That wicked men would not be obnoxious to the judgements of God if they could plead any tolerable excuſe— now of all excuſes for not doing a thing commanded, there is none more reaſonable then this, to ſay that he was not able to doe it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> You and your maſters the <hi>Remonſtrants</hi> will not part,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoc unum ad excuſationem hominis abundè ſufficiet, qùod facere, necpoteſt, nec potuit, quod non fecerit, quia obligationis ratio tum maximè omnium ceſſat, cum praetenditur ſaciendi id quod mandatur im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potentia.</hi> Act. Synod. Art. 3, 4. 142.</note> do what I can; Their words are theſe. <hi>No man is without excuſe for not doing that which he hath not power to doe. Nay this thing alone is abundantly ſufficient for his excuſe, for a commandment doth moſt of all ceaſe to oblige, when a man alledgeth that he is impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to doe it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have proved for you that this is the <hi>Arminians</hi> doctrine. Now in requitall I pray prove to me that this is <hi>Pauls,</hi> and <hi>Peters</hi> doctrine; Take heed of laying the brats of Satan at the doors of <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Paul;</hi> In your next tell me in what places <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> aſſert, that a naturall mans impotencie excuſeth him from doing his duty, whether in <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.19, 20. where <hi>we are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to dispute againſt God.</hi> Or in <hi>Rom.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>3 19.—<hi>Every mouth muſt be ſtopped.</hi> In the mean time, <hi>your old friend M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
               </hi> Bucer ſends you word by me, That our <hi>impotencie, and want of ſtrength to doe any good at all, will prove a vain excuſe.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115038:22"/>And again, when God ſhall arraign men in their own conſciences,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nequicquam ſubit excuſatio noſtraram vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium quòd ex illis nihil bont exiſtere poſſit. in Rom.</hi> 1.20. p. 86. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi homines ad ſerium judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ſui ipſorum exciverit ibi evaneſcunt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villationes ejuſmodi cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctae in</hi> Rom. 9. <hi>pag.</hi> 399.</note> all theſe cavils will fade and vaniſh, and men ſhall then condemn none but themſelves. The Saints if at any time their reaſon ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at the judgements of God, ſuppreſſe it with that, Who art thou, O man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. <hi>p.</hi> 16. <hi>Anſ.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>They repreſent it for an Error in me to ſay, Doubtles men are naturall men before they are spirituall, and yet theſe are the words of the Apostle,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.46.</p>
            <p>You complain of the ſubſcribers for rending and tearing your ſayings; but never was there a wretched paſſage ſo pitifully torn by any, as this your own paſſage is by your ſelf; Are you a bedlam that you tear your own fleſh? out of pity to you I ſhall endeavour to heal the body of this your paſſage; and give it you entire in your own words, as the Miniſters have ſet it down in their Teſtimony.</p>
            <p>It is this. <hi>Naturall men may doe ſuch things as whereunto God hath by way of promiſe annexed grace and acceptation;</hi> and immediately follows that aſtoniſhing expreſſion. (<hi>This is as dangerous an Error as</hi> Paul <hi>uttered, when he ſaid That they were no gods which were made with hands,</hi> Act. 19.26.) <hi>for doubtleſſe men are naturall men before they are ſpirituall: and ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and ſpirituall they cannot be made but by beleeving, and unto beleeving God hath promiſed grace and acceptation;</hi> Your concluſion is. <hi>If it be poſſible that naturall men may beleeve, then may they doe ſuch things whereunto God hath by way of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe annexed grace and acceptation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Reader now ſeeth, what it was in this paſſage that was repreſented as an Errour, not the words collected out of the Scripture, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.46. [<hi>Doubtleſſe men are naturall before ſpirituall</hi>] but that which went before, [<hi>naturall men may doe ſuch things whereunto God hath by way of promiſe annexed grace, becauſe they may beleeve,</hi> &amp;c.] Friend, Fear you not God? Did not your hand ſhake, and your heart tremble when you wrote that the Miniſters ſet down theſe words for the Error, <hi>Doubtles men are naturall before they are spirituall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For your poſition that <hi>naturall men may doe ſuch things whereunto God; hath by way of promiſe annexed grace:</hi> how ſhould I rejoice could I hope that the reaſon
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115038:23"/>why you conceald it in <hi>Sion Coll. viſit.</hi> was remorſe. I obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a little before that you left out the word alwaies; in ſetting down that Error (the ſame with this in other words) cited by the ſubſcribers in their Teſtimony; <hi>A naturall man by his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall principles may attain that conviction which converſion</hi> alwaies follows; I adde to what there I ſaid; I ſuppoſe by your <hi>naturall man,</hi> who you ſay <hi>doth things to which God hath an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed acceptation;</hi> you mean the ſame man that the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.8. <hi>The man in the fleſh:</hi> now that man <hi>cannot pleaſe God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Opera Anglica na contra jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. pag</hi> 8.8 <hi>Fateor non pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram nihi do uit dogma planè imptum &amp; a pertè Pelogia num obtru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i noſtrae ſcholae,</hi> &amp;c. ſed. <hi>Hominem poſſe ante ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtificatione a dum adhu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a Chriſto do nino eſt al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>us &amp; impius, facere bona opera quae fint Deo ita grata, ut bis o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Deus moveatur ad co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> creadum plenam ad ſe co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>verſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en,</hi> Rivet. <hi>Diſp.</hi> pag. 155.</note> though your <hi>naturall man doth things acceptable to God;</hi> Invert not Gods and natures order, firſt <hi>let the tree be good, and then the fruit.</hi> But know if you ſtill remain obdurate, that your good friend M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Bucer</hi> hath no more patience toward you; but in down right terms calls you <hi>Pelagian;</hi> for ſaith he, <hi>'tis an impious and a Pelagian opinion, that a man before justification, and while out of Chriſt, ſhould be able to doe good works ſo acceptable to God, that by theſe works God ſhould be moved to beſtow converſion upon him.</hi> Only I confeſſe the learned <hi>Rivet.</hi> p. 155. of <hi>his disputations,</hi> with a little more moderation calls you among the reſt a <hi>pargetted Pelagian,</hi> If I rightly En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh his words, <hi>incrustantes Pelagianiſmum.</hi> And I pray con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how little you want of <hi>meritum de congruo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you prove your poſition, That <hi>naturall men may doe ſuch good works,</hi> &amp;c. moſt lamentably; becauſe <hi>'tis poſſible</hi> (ſay you) <hi>they may beleeve.</hi> But how then (ſay I) can they doe things acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>able to God before they beleeve, if you make beleeving the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their acceptation? And who knows not but that <hi>naturall men</hi> may beleeve; <hi>viz.</hi> that they are ſuch ſubjects as God works upon, ſo as to make them beleevers? but prove that they are able to beleeve while they are <hi>naturall men.</hi> Help him logick; let <hi>fallacia a bene diviſis ad malè conjuncta</hi> be well heeded; how ſhould, your poor people know your <hi>fulla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies,</hi> when you know them not your ſelf?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>They make me an Erroneous offender,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſit. p. 16.</note> for ſaying, that to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, first that God is, ſecondly that he is a rewarder of all thoſe who diligently ſeek him, is all the faith which the Apoſtle makes abſolutely neceſſary to bring a man to God,</hi> Heb. 11 6.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Still you would fain have the Scripture counted hereticall with
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115038:23"/>your ſelf: but the Subſcribers know how to diſtinguiſh between theſe two, the holy Scriptures and your hereticall ſcriblings. Your ſelf, not the Subſcribers, make you the Erroneus offender, but not for theſe words, viz. <hi>To beleeve that God is, and that he is a rewarder,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>is all the faith which is neceſſary to bring a man to God,</hi> but for your ſaying immediately <hi>going</hi> before (which you were afraid or aſhamed to repeat,) viz. <hi>That all the world, even thoſe that have not the letter of the Goſpel, have yet ſufficient means granted them of beleeving theſe two,</hi> viz. <hi>That God is, and that he is a rewarder,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>You affirming that they who have only the heavens, the Sun, Moon, and Starres to preach the Gospel unto them, they alſo have reaſon ſufficient to judge the ſame judgement with them who have the letter of the Goſpel; for they have the Gospel</hi> (ſay you) <hi>the ſubſtance and effect of it, the willingnes of God to be reconciled to the world, preached unto them by the Apoſtles aforeſaid, the Sun, Moon, and Starres.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſtuffe is here!</p>
            <p>Have all the world ſufficient means of beleeving theſe two: 1. <hi>That God is,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.6.</note> 2. <hi>That he is a rewarder of them that diligently ſeek him?</hi> Had you underſtood that place of Scripture you would not have ſaid ſo; for the faith or belief there ſpoken of, is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſuch a faith as whereby a man may come to God with acceptation. The words are ſet down by the Apoſtle to prove <hi>that without faith no man can pleaſe God;</hi> For faith he, <hi>No man can</hi> (acceptably) come to God, unleſſe he beleeve that <hi>God is, and that he is a rewarder of them that ſeek him;</hi> ſtrongly inferring that whoſoever doth <hi>beleeve that God is, and that he is a rewarder of them that diligently ſeek him, doth come to God in a way of pleaſing him. Judicious</hi> Calvin <hi>tells you thus upon the place.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Haec eſt ratio cur citra fidem null a Deo pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceat, quia nullus unquam accedit niſi qui credit Deum eſſe, &amp; ſtatue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> remune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratorem eſſe omnibus qui eum quaerunt.</hi>
               </note> And a little after he ſaith, <hi>the Apoſtle meaneth not that men ſhould be perſwaded that there is ſome or a God, but he ſpeaks this of the true God.</hi> De vero Deo hoc praedicat, <hi>and this reward is not to be referred to the dignity of works, but to faith.</hi> Haec remuneratio non ad operum dignitatem vel pretium, ſed ad fidem refertur. <hi>Calv.</hi> in loc. And <hi>Paraeus upon that place will inform you that thoſe two heads of faith, That God is, and that God is a rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of them that diligently ſeek him, are not to be underſtood
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115038:24"/>Philoſophically, but Theologically; that the eternall God is Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Son and holy Ghoſt, and that he is a rewarder of them that ſeek him Evangelically by faith in Chriſt, with the benefits of the Gospel, pardon, adoption, ſanctification, glory,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And can Heathens by the Sun Moon and Starres doe this? can they by the light of nature beleeve a trinity of Perſons in unity of Eſſence? if they doe, they are better then your godly perſons,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hag.</hi> pag 36</note> 
               <hi>who you ſay are holy and walk with God, and yet beleeve not that God is one in three perſons.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ad co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nitiene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>per create<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras ex naturae lumine non ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ducimur, niſi quatenus Deus eſt earum prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipium &amp; cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa non au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>em earum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>auſa, niſi per divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam, ſuam cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutem omnil us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>warem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> per creaturas cognitionem conſequinon valemus niſi eam quae patri &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; spi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>i <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>cto ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t communis quo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>: per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reaturas ad cognoſcendam per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonarum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> non poſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>gere.</hi> G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>de</hi> Trin.</note> None (ſaith <hi>Gerard</hi>) can be led to the knowledge of God by the creatures, but only ſo farre forth as God is their cauſe; Now God is their cauſe by a divine power common to the three perſons; therefore by the creatures we can onely attain to knowledge of thoſe things which are <hi>common</hi> to the three Perſons, wherefore cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly by the creatures we can never attain to the knowledge of the diſtinction of perſons. Name one heathen who did moſt diligently ſearch into nature, that did by the inſpection of the creature, know there was a trinity of perſons.</p>
            <p>And can the heathens by the works of creation have the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries of a mediator? and have Chriſt made known to them? and beleeve in him? I am ſure you never learned this of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dicimus fide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in Chriſtum non ſemper requiri ad juſtificatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, ſed fid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>pliciter, ut reſtatur Apo ſtolus,</hi> Heb. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>in quo et<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n additur, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> dam req<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> credere qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Deus ſit &amp; quod ſit rem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nera <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t illoru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> qui ipſum quaerunt de fide verò in Chriſtum nulla vel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inima fit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fot. lib. de ſat. Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> cap. to. p. 17<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> who ſaith that <hi>faith comes by hearing,</hi> Rom. 10. Or are you of <hi>Smalcius</hi> his judgement, who faith that <hi>faith in Chriſt is not alwaies required to juſtification; but faith ſimply,</hi> and he proves it out of this very Scripture that you have here alledg'd, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. for the faith of heathens; <hi>Sir, blame me not if I be jealous of you, as of one that favours ſocinianiſme;</hi> Sure I am, you muſt either hold that heathens muſt attain faith <hi>in Chriſt</hi> by the enjoying of ſun moon and ſtarres; or that the faith of the 11. of <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. which (you ſay) the heathens doe attain by the ſun moon and ſtartes, is not a faith in Chriſt, and then welfare <hi>Smalcius;</hi> In your next, I pray manifeſt your judgement herein.</p>
            <p>Or of whom learned you this opinion, that they who have
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115038:24"/>
               <hi>only the ſun moon and ſtarres,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Impoſſibile eſt pervenire ad ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, pervenire ad aeternam vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam, niſi audie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris evargelium, id<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> adminiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum per homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, nam de praedicatione Evangelij Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus hic l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>quitur quam dominus per Apoſtolos ſuos ado. ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtravit.</hi> Bucer. <hi>in</hi> Rom. 10. <hi>Act. Synod. Artic.</hi> 2. <hi>Col. Hag. art.</hi> 2. <hi>Ad Arg.</hi> 5. pag. 179. <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> p. 17. <hi>Anſ.</hi>
               </note> &amp;c. <hi>to preach the Geſpel unto them, have ſufficient means of beleeving?</hi> Certainly M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Bucer</hi> never was your Maſter, who on <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. ſaith, <hi>It's impoſſible to attain to ſaith, to aeternall life, unleſſe thou heareſt the Gospel, and that admi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>istred by man, for</hi> Paul <hi>here ſpeaks of the preaching of the Goſpel which God adminiſtred by his Apoſtles;</hi> But whoſe ſcholler are you now? Friend you are to blame to put me out of my old way, for I would fain have found a ſchoolmaſter among the <hi>Arminians</hi> for you, but the truth is you have now outgon <hi>your Maſters;</hi> They indeed ſay that <hi>God calls all with a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon calling by which men may be made fit to hear the Goſpel, in which ſalvation is offered,</hi> &amp;c. but they never dream'd of a Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel <hi>by Sun, Moon, and Starres,</hi> nay, when preſſed at the <hi>confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence at Hague,</hi> to ſhew the <hi>univerſality</hi> of the preaching of the Goſpel, though they have many ſhifts and cavils, yet this of your Preachers never came into their minde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let all my ſayings be drawn together, and the rigideſt extracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made, there will be found the ſame ſpirit of errour (if yet it were errour) in Mr</hi> John Ball, <hi>Intituled,</hi> A <hi>Treatiſe of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace.—pag.</hi> 44. <hi>of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>courſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot wonder that you who would fain father your errours upon <hi>Scripture,</hi> are in this kinde induſtrious alſo to abuſe holy and learned M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Ball;</hi> lay not your egges of errour in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Balls</hi> neſt, thinking that by the warmth of his reputation to have them hatched.</p>
            <p>The words of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Ball</hi> are theſe. <hi>No man is hindered from beleeving through the difficulty or unreaſonablenes of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, or through his own ſimple infirmity, as being willing to beleeve, but not able, which inability deſerves pity, but he doth not beleeve becauſe he will not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is here, that gives you the leaſt countenance in your er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours? M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Ball</hi> ſaith and that truly, <hi>that unwillingneſſe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve hinders a man from beleeving, but he doth not ſay that any man of himſelf can be willing;</hi> for pag. 226. <hi>having aſſerted that man is unable to beleeve,</hi> and in the ſame page, <hi>that it is of grace to be inabled to beleeve,</hi> he preſently adds, <hi>that mands not further from beleeving then deſire to beleeve.</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>B.</hi> grants that it's mans fault that he diſſents from grace calling him, but
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115038:25"/>where, ſaith he, it is in mans power to conſent to grace calling him: and if he will not ſay ſo, he cannot be of your faith, who main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that man hath <hi>ability</hi> to <hi>beleeve,</hi> and may ſo <hi>improve his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall</hi> abilities that converſion alwaies will follow, and <hi>if man had not power to beleeve. God were unjuſt to command it.</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Ball</hi> blames mans unwillingneſſe to beleeve, and you like an <hi>acute logician</hi> thence conclude mans ſufficiency. 'Twere eaſie to ſhew as great a diſſonancy between you and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Ball</hi> in this point, as there is an harmony between you and the Remonſtrants: Take it in theſe four or five paſſages. 1. You ſay, <hi>Div. Auth.</hi> p. 168. <hi>That if man ſhould be deprived of all ability to beleeve, and yet God ſhould be still moving and perſwading men to beleeve, this would be harder then injuſtice it ſelf; As for a King to cauſe a mans leggs to be cut off, and yet command him to run a race.</hi> And you ſay <hi>that mans inability to do any thing that God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, is a very fair and reaſonable excuſe for not doing it,</hi> Div. Auth. <hi>p.</hi> 201. <hi>But Mr</hi> Ball <hi>ſaith,</hi> pag. 245, 246. of the Cou. of Gr. <hi>That an impoſſible thing to us, may be, and is the object of Gods command, and of his deſire.</hi> Nay (in the ſame place) <hi>the Lord commands and deſires the converſion of many obſtinate, impenitent perſons who have the means of grace, whom for their preſent contempt, he doth blinde and harden; If impoſſible be not the object of Gods will in this fence,</hi> viz. <hi>impoſſible in reſpect of ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; he that by custome in evil hath contracted an habit that he cannot but ſin, ſhould not offend, and he that is carried with the moſt violence of minde to evil, ſhould be leaſt evil,</hi> pag. 247. he ſaith, <hi>that God may juſtly withhold the graces of his ſpirit from thoſe that are invited in the Miniſtery,</hi> and pag. 248. <hi>The Lord doth earneſtly again and again call upon impenitent and obſtinate ſinners to repent and beleeve, when as yet in his juſt judgement he hardens their hearts that they cannot repent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas you call mans inability a fair excuſe for not doing: M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Ball</hi> ſaith, <hi>pag.</hi> 249. that <hi>though God do not enable men to come to him, yet if men reaſon thus, Why doth he then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat us and perſwade us?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>they may as well plead against the foreknowledge of God, If God foreknew that men would not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, why doth he intreat us? and he concludes that theſe are ignorant and blinde imaginations.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:115038:25"/>
            <p>You ſay <hi>pag.</hi> 26. Div. Auth. <hi>Naturall men may doe ſuch things as whereunto God hath promiſed acceptation; and upon improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of naturall abilities grace alwaies follows,</hi> p. 200.</p>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Ball</hi> ſaith, p. 237. <hi>That they who uſe well their ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall gifts, ſhall be enriched with an increaſe, but he ſaith alſo, that men unregenerate cannot uſe their naturall gifts ſo as to procure acceptation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You hold that they who have only <hi>the Sun, Moon, and Starres, and the goodneſſe of God in guiding of the world, have ſufficient means of beleeving granted to them,</hi> &amp;c. But M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Ball</hi> ſaith; <hi>God exacts of the Gentiles given up to the vanity of their mindes, that they ſhould ſeek him in the way wherein he will be found, if they would be ſaved, when they have not means ſufficient to bring them to the knowledge of the truth.</hi> And pag. 247. <hi>Many Infidels have departed this life, before they had means to come to the knowledge of Jeſus Christ; and God denies to ſome both means and grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your erroneous writings are as repugnant to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Ball,</hi> as if you had laid his book before you not for <hi>citation</hi> but <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the opinion which this grand ſubſcription voteth an error in me about a naturall mans power to good ſupernaturall,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſit. <hi>p.</hi> 20.</note> I deſire the whole covent of two and fifty, with all that dogmatize with them, to know that it is no new doctrine in the Reformed Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Think you that the Subſcribers take you to be the author of this errour?
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> did not your ſelf even now acquit <hi>this generation from the invention of it</hi> and the other errours, by the lamentable ſubterfuge of only a revivall of them? who knows not that the Church hath been anciently diſturbed with your doctrine about <hi>freewill to good ſupernaturall?</hi> The <hi>Centuriſts</hi> obſerve that very early was the faith of Chriſt corrupted in this point; The errour of <hi>Pelagius</hi> was born before <hi>John Goodwin;</hi> may it was confuted and condemned in many counſells, it rebreathed in the <hi>Maſſilians,</hi> was entertained by ſome Schoolmen, and varniſhed over by <hi>Arminius,</hi> before ever you were a well willer to it. Inſtead of denying the <hi>ſtrangeneſſe</hi> of it, you ſhould have proved the <hi>truth of is;</hi> and inſtead of pleading that it hath been in the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115038:26"/>Church, have proved it the doctrine of the Church; But why <hi>ſhun you novelty?</hi> This is the way to looſe your <hi>Athenian Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelytes,</hi> who love <hi>novelty</hi> better <hi>then truth;</hi> And how prove you it is no new doctrine?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sioa Col</hi> viſi. p 21.</note>
            </p>
            <p>You ſay that <hi>There is not an hairs breadth of power to ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall good more attributed by me to naturall men, then is clearly aſſerted by</hi> Paulus Teſtardus <hi>Pastor of the Reformed Church of</hi> Blois.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> 1. <hi>But of what ſtanding was</hi> Teſtardus? <hi>his Treatiſe printed</hi> 1633<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>ſpeaks him but of yeſterday, and too young to be the author of an old doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Who was this <hi>Testardus,</hi> that his authority is ſo praeva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent with you?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vinlicie Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demptionis. Ep.</hi> to the Reader.</note> Though you ſo highly prize him, yet my Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend friend M <hi>Stalbam,</hi> whoſe judgement in the matter of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline though I am not fully inform'd oſt, yet for modeſty and learning he much exceeds you; and he ſo far abhors theſe opinions of yours, that he aſſerts concerning this <hi>Teſtardus</hi> (upon through examination of him) that his <hi>colours are the colours of grace, while he fights for nature, and of a covenant of grace, while he ſights for a covenant of works and nature;</hi> That <hi>he findes the univerſaliſts of this time: have lighted their candle (after</hi> Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius <hi>was stincking in the ſnuff and ſocket) from this</hi> Teſtardus; Nay he conceives alſo, that even <hi>Oats</hi> that infamous Sectary ſuckt ſeverall errours from <hi>Teſtardus.</hi> The very time of the edition of <hi>Teſtardus</hi> was, when we were peſtered with a number of ſuch <hi>Testarduſſes,</hi> when the good work carried on, was the advancement of <hi>Arminian</hi> and <hi>Popiſh</hi> dictates above the Scripture; and I know not whether it was long after that time, that your ſelf began <hi>to dogmatize and ſow your tares</hi> in your pariſh of <hi>Colemanstreet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>You ſay that</hi> Teſtardus <hi>his book was approved by two of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Preſbytery;</hi> but if the authority of a province of Miniſters be (as you ſay truly) a weak <hi>ſupport for the judgements of men in matters of doctrine,</hi> ſurely the teſtimony of <hi>two Miniſters</hi> is none of the ſtrongeſt grounds to build your aſſertions upon.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Did not your heart ſmite you when you wrote that the doctrine of <hi>Testardus</hi> is the received doctrine of <hi>the Reformed Churches in France,</hi> and aſſerted for Orthodox by a province
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115038:26"/>of Miniſters in <hi>France.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Spanhem de gratiâ univerſ. p.</hi> 31. <hi>Anatome Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianiſmi enoda tio graviſſima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum queſt.</hi>
               </note> Why cite you not the <hi>confeſſions of the Gallicane churches?</hi> Are you a ſtranger to the <hi>ſynod of Dort,</hi> confirmed by the <hi>Synods of France? to the writings of</hi> Pet. Moli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus <hi>the most noted Miniſter of the French Churches, and deſigned by them as their delegate to that Synod?</hi> —And whence have you it that the province of Miniſters <hi>in</hi> Orleance <hi>approved of Teſtardus his writings?</hi> Did you never read that it was prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited in the Synod <hi>of Alenzon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Spanhem de gratiâ univerſ. pag.</hi> 1.</note> to publiſh any ſuch tractates as this of <hi>Teſtardus:</hi> and what hindered that there was no more ſeverity uſed? and with what face can you aver that treatiſe, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by a <hi>Synod in France?</hi> whereas therefore you ſcoff at the ſubſcribers for ſaying that the Confeſſion of faith adviſed by the Aſſembly of Divines, is agreable to the Confeſſious of other Churches; You are deſired in your next to ſhew in any of theſe points whereof we are now ſpeaking, any materiall difference between their confeſſions and ours: The confeſſion of faith pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by the Aſſembly to the Parliament, agrees to the Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the laſt named Churches, though not to the <hi>ſemipelagian Theorems of a dough-baked Teſtardus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall add no more but this, to tell you, that when you went about to make <hi>Teſtardus your Patron,</hi> you ſpake to the whole <hi>Colledge or Covent</hi> (as you call it) <hi>of the</hi> 52. <hi>and all that dogmatize with them againſt your opinion,</hi> In which paſſage you bring in (and that truly) the whole number of 52 as teſtifying againſt you, whereas <hi>pag.</hi> the ſecond, you ſay, that neither D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Gouge,</hi> nor M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Calamy,</hi> nor M <hi>Caſe,</hi> nor M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Cranford,</hi> nor ſundry others were either the Authours or ſubſcribers of the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony. A crazy conſcience,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sion Col. viſie. p.</hi> 23.</note> and a brittle memory are very ill companions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the proof of your doctrine about naturall mans free will, and power to good ſupernaturall, you cite a paſſage out of</hi> Bucer <hi>on</hi> Rom. 2, 14. <hi>and you ſay that the paſſage is fuller of the ſpirit of that opinion which the ſubſcribers reckon among hereſies,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> then any paſſage in your writing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have proved that <hi>Bucer</hi> ſhakes you off, as a bold beggar, is aſhamed of you, and cals you <hi>Pelagian,</hi> and theres nothing in this paſſage of <hi>Bucer</hi> like your opinion, with what engines did you draw your concluſion from <hi>Bucers</hi> premiſes? <hi>Bucer</hi> ſaith not <hi>A na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115038:27"/>man hath power to bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eve, That the Sun, Moon and Start are Preachers of the Gospel: or that if naturall men be unable to beleeve, they are excuſable, or that God ſhould be a tyrant in commanding men to do that, which they have not ability to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form.</hi> What doth he ſay that looks this way? If any thing could have been wreſted from this place that agreed with you, yet you ſhew nothing but extream ignorance or impudency to alledge an authour for you, the whole ſtrain of whoſe writings are ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly oppoſite unto you.</p>
            <p>But in this place which you alledge, had <hi>Bucer</hi> countenanced your opinion, you would have told the Reader wherein the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement between you and <hi>Bucer</hi> ſteed, or have grounded an argument upon ſome of <hi>Bucers</hi> words for your opinion, but alas! you do none of all this, you ſay that your doctrines and <hi>Bucers</hi> agree, but here's not a ſyllable to prove how or wherein; Reader I pray obſerve the harmony between <hi>Bucer</hi> &amp; <hi>I. G. Bucer</hi> ſaith here, <hi>that God in no age left men deſtitute of the doctrine of ſalvation (as you tranſlate it)</hi> which he underſtands of the Law, which is in it ſelf <hi>doctrina ſalutaris</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Profeſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truae ſalutaris, boc eſt recte vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i,</hi> Bucer. <hi>enar. ſect.</hi> 4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.</note>, and of which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaks in that place, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.14. on which <hi>Bucer</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but you aſſert the Goſpel to have been known to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bucer</hi> ſaith here, that God ſo <hi>bedeweth nature with his light, that they only remain ſtrangers unto righteouſneſſe, who wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly put it from them:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you, that man hath power willingly to embrace this righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and not to put it from him; to which <hi>Bucer</hi> ſpeaks, expreſſely contrary in the ſame Chapter, <hi>They have</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>light enough to enfirce ſelf-condemnation for Walking wickedly, but not ſufficient to glorifie God as they know</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deus certâ per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>em quibusvis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or talibus impertit tam ampla qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ut qui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ra ve vivu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tande<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n coademnare co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantur, at nendum ſuffi cieme eò, ut Deum ſicut cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcunt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am queant gio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rificare.</hi> In Rom. 2.23. <hi>Veru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n qurdem tſlu: reminem poſſe, niſi Deo lucem ſuam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſundente eſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius, eoque a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gente ad ſe &amp; trabente homi num an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mus.</hi> in Rom. 1.30.</note>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bucer</hi> ſaith, <hi>Did the Gentiles not voluntarily put away the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of righteouſneſſe, they ſhould ſooner be taught by an Angel, then be ſuffered to be ignorant of Chriſt,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>You ſay, that they have ability to do what is righteous and to beleeve</hi> (which <hi>Bucer</hi> as you heard even now flatly demeth) And for an Angel to reveal Chriſt, that would be according to M. <hi>Goodwin,</hi> ſuperfluous, <hi>the Sun, Moon</hi> and <hi>Stars are Apoſtles,</hi> and all to them the Goſpel is to us, in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Goodwins</hi> opinion.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:115038:27"/>
            <p>And (where indeed lieth your miſerable miſtake of <hi>Bucer</hi> In this place) you ſaid even now,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Soli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> babentiiut el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ttionu do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ſcientta vitae commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>catur, &amp; ab ijs qui cocare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant per praedi. calum etiam hoc quod divi. nae cognitionls videntur habere auforetur quia reprobi poſt coxtemptum verbum (quod nequeunt reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere) magis excaecantur.</hi> Bucer. in Mat. 13. <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Col.</hi> viſited p. 23.</note> that converſion <hi>alwaies follows upon the improvement of naturals, Bucer</hi> though he ſaith that <hi>God would ſend an Angel to inſtruct thoſe that did not put from them the deſire of righteouſneſſe, yet holds that from the gift of Gods election only, and not the improvement of naturals, this manifeſtation of Chriſt, and ſalvation through him to proceed, and from them who want that gift of election, ſhall that which they had by the word preached be taken away;</hi> becauſe (ſaith he) the <hi>reprobate after the word contemned</hi> (which they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not receive) <hi>are more blinded:</hi> by the way, tell me in your next, whether <hi>Bucer</hi> makes not God a <hi>cruell tyrant,</hi> in ſaying that <hi>the reprobate contemn the word,</hi> and <hi>cannot receive</hi> it, though God command them to do it.</p>
            <p>You ſtill labour to make your own face clean by throwing dirt in <hi>Bucers.</hi> You ſay <hi>that Bucer conceiveth that Paul offered this to the conſideration of the Jews, that the Gentiles even before Chriſt was revealed unto them, were partakers of true righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. And this</hi> you ſay <hi>is a ſaying ten degrees beyond the line of any of yours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your aim is here to make <hi>Bucer</hi> ſeem a Gyant, that you,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by him, may but ſeem a Dwarf in hereſie; you ſhould have laid the parallel right, and then for degrees you might have blotted out ten, and have ſet down an hundred.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts were not ſo cruell by a thouſand parts in digging up of <hi>Bucers</hi> body, when dead, and buried, as you in labouring to bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry his name, while it is yet living, and rather then his name ſhall want a burying place, to make your own throat an open ſepulcher.</p>
            <p>You deſire that the reader ſhould beleeve it was <hi>Bucers</hi> judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the Gentiles could be <hi>justified without Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Legis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliter accipit praoſſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae quae lex de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Buc. in loc.</note> becauſe <hi>Bucer</hi> ſaith, they were made partakers of true righteouſneſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt was revealed to them (and if this be not the opinion which you deſire to affix to <hi>Bucer,</hi> 'tis ſo far from being ten de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree beyond yours, that it is a thouſand degrees ſhort of yours) but by righteouſneſſe <hi>Bucer</hi> only underſtands the duties of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe commanded in the Law.</p>
            <p>But you do wickedly to ſeem willing, that the reader ſhould
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115038:28"/>beleeve,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoſtolus prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipue o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>but wodis laberat oſtendere extra Chriſtum nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los non perditot eſſe non minus julaeos quam Gentes,</hi> Enar. Sect 4. cap. 2. Rom.</note> that <hi>Bucer</hi> did ever imagine any could be juſtified out of Chriſt, you may conſult him in the <hi>Enar. Sect.</hi> 4. cap. 2. on <hi>Rom.</hi> where he aſſerts <hi>that all are loſt out of Chriſt.</hi> If <hi>Bucer</hi> be a friend to your opinions, I know not who is an enemy; And I am conſident the Miniſters of the Province of <hi>Babylon,</hi> that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned <hi>Bucer,</hi> as you ſay, for an heretick, and a man of rotten judgement, dig'd him out of his grave, and made a ſacrifice by fire of his dead, and buried corps, unto the <hi>Genius</hi> of their bloudy Religion, would have ſuffered your bones to have reſted in their grave, if they had not rather been digd up, to be reſerved as holy reliques, to be enſhrined according to the <hi>Genius</hi> of their fooliſh ſuperſtition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It were eaſy to fill many pages with paſſages from other Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Authours,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſit. p. 23.</note> who have delivered many things fully conſonant with what I have written.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You have a good faculty at filling of pages;
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> A childe can blur paper, And for full pages out of the Orthodox, Let me have one page half fild to begin withall, agreeing with thoſe your opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, which are tranſcribed by the ſubſcribers, and it ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe you the labour of filling many; If your Authouts, which you ſay you can produce be of M. <hi>Ball</hi> and M. <hi>Bucers</hi> minde, you will but abuſe them and they will accuſe you; for you have brought theſe two to bleſſe your ſelf, and curſe the ſubſcribers, whereas they have done the contrary altogether.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nor were it a matter of much more difficulty to bring antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it ſelf,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sion. Col.</hi> viſit. p. 24.</note> and particularly thoſe very authours who were the greatest oppoſers of</hi> Pelagius, <hi>as</hi> Hierom, Auſtin, Proſper, <hi>with their mouths wide open in approbation of the ſame things, for which I am arraigned at the Tribunall of</hi> Sinon-Colledge.</p>
            <p>For your ſcoff of <hi>Sinon Colledge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auſ.</hi>
               </note> If it be <hi>Sinon-Colledge,</hi> 'tis ſo ſince you viſited it, nor did it ever favour of a <hi>Sinon</hi> till your Biſhops foot ſtept into it. I know none, that deſerve to be called <hi>Sinons,</hi> but Traitors to a City, and who they were you may finde out without comming to Sion-Colledge.</p>
            <p>You come to the fathers for patronage, being caſt of, both by <hi>Ball,</hi> and <hi>Bucer,</hi> But they afford you no relief, only every thing would fain live, yet you finde no more help from them then a
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:115038:28"/>man neer drowning by a deep and violent torrent, doth from a fearther in the water departing from him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You ſay the Fathers approve of, and couſſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſame things for which you are arraigned at the Tribunall of</hi> Sinon-Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſit. p.24.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Ther's not one of the paſſages quoted out of the fathers,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> that give the leaſt ſhadow of an approbation, to any of thoſe errours tranſcribed by the ſubſcribers, Nor can I imagine any reaſon why you ſhould alledge any of theſe paſſages unleſſe it be, becauſe you finde the <hi>word Liberum arbitrium,</hi> in ſome of them which may be uſed againſt you as well as for you. You quote the fathers for your patronage, and aſſerting the ſame things with you, but what is in the fathers that is, but like thoſe your paſſages <hi>A naturall men hath power to beleeve: If God did command men to beleeve, they not having abilities, God ſhould be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> tyrant. The want of abilitie is a law full excuſe for now-performance; man may ſo improve his naturals, as that true converſion ſhall alwaies fellow: That the Sun, Moon, and Stars, are Preachers of the Gospel,</hi> &amp;c. Let the Fathers ſayings, and yours be compared; but herein you deal with the Fathers, as before with <hi>Bucer,</hi> when you alledg'd him; you tell me that Antiquity is on your ſide, and ſet down barely two, or three broken ends of ſentences, groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding no argument upon thoſe paſſages for your opinions as indeed you cannot; you ſeeming rather ambitious to be accounted able to read a peece of the Fathers writings, then able to underſtand them.</p>
            <p>As you have cited the Fathers <hi>moſt impertinently,</hi> (which by and by ſhall fully appear) ſo moſt <hi>imperfectly</hi> and ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>edly as if you did not like an ingenuous gueſt expect a meal from them but like a beggar their ſcraps and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>agments only. <hi>Jer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m ſaith M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaeorum eſt hominum damdare naturum, &amp; liberum au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erre arbitrium, The Manishees take away free will</hi> but why leave you out that whichfollows, <hi>&amp; adjutorium Deitollere and take away the help of God?</hi> Is it becauſe your maſters the <hi>Remonſtrants</hi> do ſo, or becauſe you would make way for your accuſation, following againſt the Miniſters by obſcuring <hi>the Manichees</hi> doctrine.</p>
            <p>Why leave you out <hi>ruſum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, apertiſſimae, eſt inſaniae hoc homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem dicere eſſe, quod Deus eſt,</hi> Its madneſſe to ſay that man is
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:115038:29"/>what God is, in which words <hi>Hierom</hi> rejects the opinion of the <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lagians,</hi> which is alſo years,—In the next quotation out of <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om</hi> why break you off at theſe words <hi>Damnetur ille qui dam. nat,</hi> and add not <hi>Caeterum non differimus a b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utis quod liberi arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trij conditi ſumus, ſed ipſum liberum arbitrium Dei nititur aux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ilio, we differ not only from beasts becauſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we were made with free will,</hi> which h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpeaks in oppoſition to the <hi>Manichees, but in that the help of God in all things ſustains it.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exeo quod no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> add<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>liſti vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>negare.</hi> Heer, adverſ. Pelag. <hi>lib.</hi> 1.</note> Which he utters againſt the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> you expreſſe the one and conceal the other, and if <hi>Hierom</hi> may be heard, in <hi>as much as you add it not, you ſeem to deny it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why do you ſo mangle <hi>Auſtin,</hi> why break you off at <hi>Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> hoc neſcit?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aag de Grat. &amp; lib. Arbitr.</hi>
               </note> who knows not this? <hi>God would not command that which he knew man could not perform; Who knows not this?</hi> and add not with him, ſed ideo jubet, <hi>&amp;c. but God therefore ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times commands ſome things which we cannot do, that we might know what to beg of him;</hi> Was it to conceal his judgement in what ſence the Law is impoſſible? namely, although poſſible to Grace, yet impoſſible to corrupt man? Or was it to make way for the next paſſage you alledge out of him. <hi>We execrate the blaſphemy of thoſe who affirm that God enjoyns any thing that is impoſſible; as if you had a minds to have the reader think that</hi> Auſtin <hi>voteth Chriſt a blasphemer for ſaying</hi> Mat. 19. <hi>It is as eaſy for a camel to go thorow the eye of a needle,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>or the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle a blasp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emer for ſaying,</hi> Rom. 8.3. <hi>That which was impoſſible to the law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas you pretend, that <hi>Auſtin</hi> and <hi>Hierom</hi> defend you againſt what is laid to your charge about free-will, you moſt groſſely miſtake, either through weakneſſe, or wilfulneſſe. For the fathers aſſert the being, and nature of free-will only, and not its power to ſupernaturall good, in all the paſſages, which you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge (and you might to that purpoſe have produced an hundred more) out of them. I might acquaint the reader, that your thredbare quotations are commonly made uſe of, by the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> and <hi>Arminia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> even <hi>uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> adnauſeam</hi> (out of the latter where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by comparing your writings with theirs, I have cauſe to think you borrow theſe paſſages) But to let that paſſe, though <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and <hi>Hierom</hi> againſt the <hi>Manichees</hi> maintained the nature of free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115038:29"/>will, yet 'tis as true, that againſt the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> they denied the <hi>abilities</hi> of free-will to good ſupernaturall, as being captive, and dead; of this latter you wiſely take no notice at all, as making directly againſt you, though there are hundreds, not to ſay thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of inſtances to that purpoſe to be found in them; And thus the learned and orthodex divines of the reformed Churches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad underſtand both <hi>Austin</hi> and <hi>Hierom</hi> when alledged by Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts and Arminians as writing for free-will.
<note place="margin">Thus alſo <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot</hi> and <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaux, Abbot</hi> againſt Biſhop. <hi>Pridea. Lect.</hi> 4. <hi>de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſionis modo. Si non eſt libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Arbitrium quomodo Deus juditat mudum.</hi> Aug. ad val. ep. 46. Vid Riv. To. 2. p. 183.</note> 
               <hi>Rivetus</hi> and <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leus</hi> two famouſly learned writers among the Proteſtants ſhall ſuffice for inſtancing; <hi>Baily</hi> the leſuite objected out of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> to prove free-will, that very place againſt the Proteſtants which you alledge againſt the Miniſters (<hi>Baily</hi> the Jeſuite is more your Patron then either <hi>Ball</hi> or <hi>Bucer</hi>) The place is this, If there be no <hi>free-will, how ſhall Godiudge the world?</hi> This place <hi>Rives</hi> underſtands of the naturall being of free-will; For (ſaith he) <hi>If man were turned into a ſtone or a black, or a bruit creature, he ſhould be exempted from Gods iudgement, but ſince when he acts out of deliberation, he chuſeth and willeth what pleaſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he deſervedly gives an account to God of his actions:</hi> But <hi>Rivet</hi> proves at large from many places which he citeth out of <hi>Augustine,</hi> that this place alledged both by you and <hi>Baily,</hi> makes nothing for free-will to good ſupernaturall, as from that place in <hi>Auſtin</hi> where he ſaith, man hath loſt his <hi>free-will to love God, by the greatneſſe of the firſt ſin,</hi> and from that place <hi>free-will was once given by God, which being by our own fault loſt, cannot be reſtored but by God,</hi> and he concludes that <hi>Sexcenta, many hundreds of places might he alledged to that purpoſe out of him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Molinaus</hi> being charged by that angry <hi>Arminian Corvinus</hi> for deſtroying free-will,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Wal. oper.</hi> p. 95. <hi>Tom.</hi> 2.</note> and joyning hands with the <hi>Manichees</hi> and the <hi>Priſcillianiſts</hi> (an imputation by M. <hi>Goodwin</hi> laid upon the ſubſcribers in this Pamphlet) <hi>Walleus returns</hi> him this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. We ſay with <hi>Jerom</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Thou doſt in vain perſwade the ignorant that we condemn free-will, nay let him be condemned that condemns it, but immediately</hi> he gives the reaſon why and how both <hi>Jerom</hi> and himſelf did allow of free-will, not in regard of its abilities to good ſupernaturall, but becauſe (ſaith he) <hi>he denieth man to be created according to the image of God, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies him to be adorned with this naturall faculty of free-will.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:115038:30"/>
            <p>In your next I pray cite <hi>Rivet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. p. 45. <hi>Aug. contr. du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p Pelag l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 2 <hi>Hierom. al Cteſip.</hi> ep. c 3. <hi>Ieſuitae mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheiſmi inſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt qui cuor ſanctli illis viris loquuntur quaſt cum mamcheis ſentirent qui liberum arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trium ad bonil ſupernaturals amiſſun con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teeduat.</hi> Riv. Tom. 1. p. 177. <hi>Col</hi> 1. <hi>Quod porro ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jung is noſtros eſſentiam uberi arbitrij todere cum Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tchae is ſolita <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alu maia eſt</hi> Walleus <hi>de Praed.</hi> p 65. Springlius <hi>de Hodiern baereſ.</hi> par. 1. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Calumni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; Blaſphemia eſt gratiam veram liberum noſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> arbitrium ad omnemalu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n procl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve corri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentem, arguere Manichaeiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>i omne libe um arbi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rium tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. Sion Col.</hi> viſited <hi>p</hi> 25. <hi>Anſw.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Wall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> for patrons of free-will alſo.</p>
            <p>Your accuſation that we confute <hi>Pelagianiſm:</hi> by pure <hi>Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheiſme,</hi> as a worn calumnie. 'Tis as old as <hi>Pelagius</hi> he did caſt it upon <hi>Auſtin, Reclamabis, &amp; dices nos Manichaeorum dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma ſequi;</hi> you will ſay that we follow the opinion of the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nichees,</hi> and upon <hi>Hierom,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>Hoc non mihi ſed Apoſtolo imputa,</hi> Lay this imputation (ſaith he) upon the <hi>Apoſtle, not</hi> upon me. And of the frequency of this accuſation <hi>of Manicheiſme,</hi> againſt the holy man <hi>Auguſtine</hi> Read at large in <hi>Rivetus</hi> his <hi>Catholicus Orthodoxus,</hi> Tom. 2. de <hi>lib. Arbitr.</hi> Nay the Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites caſt the ſame reproach upon the Proteſtants, and the <hi>Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> upon the learned <hi>aſſertours</hi> of grace againſt free-will, which <hi>John Goodwin</hi> doth here upon the Miniſters. The <hi>Jeſuites</hi> faith <hi>Rivet</hi> charge thoſe with <hi>Manicheiſme,</hi> who ſpeak, as the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (thoſe holy men) ſpake. And they ſuggeſt that <hi>they who contend, that freewill is loſt as to good ſupernaturall, doe agree with the Manichces,</hi> And the learned <hi>Wallaus</hi> tells <hi>Corvinus</hi> the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minian that its an old reproach; I ſhall add, that this abominable calumnie againſt the faithfull ſervants of Chriſt, either proceeds from unparalleld impudency, you ſpeaking againſt your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, or inexcuſable ignorance that you underſtand not what you ſay, or whereof you affirm, I mean, know not what <hi>Manicheiſme</hi> is,</p>
            <p>But <hi>Springlius de hodiernis haereſib,</hi> hath ſufficiently anſwered this imputation. Truly aſſerting <hi>that it is blasphemy to accuſe the true grace of God working in us, and amending our will which is only prone to evill, of</hi> Mauicheiſme, <hi>taking away all our free-will,</hi> If God have not given you over to a ſpirit of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, you will ſay ſo too, or more in your next, in which I deſire you to prove this your odiouſlly falſe accuſation,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The question between Pelagius and the Fathers, was not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man had freedome of will in respect of good or evill, but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men notwithstwnding their freedome of will did not ſtill ſtand in need of the adjutory of grace, both for the performance of, and perſeverance in what was good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your miſtake here is pitifull, not to ſay palpable; for the great queſtion between <hi>Hierom, Auſtin, and Pelagius,</hi> was not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:115038:30"/>the will did ſtand in need of the <hi>adjutory</hi> of grace, for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of good; but what kinde of <hi>adjutory</hi> it was,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Liberum arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trium babere not dicimus, quod in omnibus bonis operibus divino ſemper adiuvaiur oux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ilio<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cont. Pel, lib.</hi> 1 6.31. <hi>Liberum ſic con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitemur arbitri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, ut dicomus no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſemperindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere Dei auxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio</hi> Ibid <hi>cap</hi> 33, <hi>Nos ownino ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bil boni facere poſſumus ſine Deo</hi> ib, <hi>c.</hi> 35. <hi>It a bominis laudamus natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, ut Dei ſemper gratiae addamus auxilium.</hi> ib <hi>c.</hi> 37. <hi>Anathema, quiſentit, vel docet gratiam Dei, non ſolun per ſingulas boran &amp; per ſingula momenta, ſed etiam per ſingulos actus noſtios non eſſe neceſſariam, &amp; qui banc conantur anſerre, poenas ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientur aeternas</hi> 10. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> of which the will did ſtand in need, and wherein grace was an <hi>adjutory</hi> to the will, was the queſtion controverted; For <hi>Pelagius</hi> himſelf granted the neceſſity of the adjutory of grace, therefore this could not be the queſtion.</p>
            <p>We ſay (ſaith he) <hi>that we have a free will which is alwaies in all good things aſſiſted with the help of God.</hi> Aug. cont. <hi>Pelag. &amp; Caeleſt. lib.</hi> 1, cap. 31.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We ſo confeſſe free will, as that we ſay we alwaies ſtand in need of the help of God,</hi> ibid. cap. 33.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We can do nothing without the help of God.</hi> ibid. cap. 35.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We ſo praiſe nature as that we alwaies add the help of the grace of God.</hi> cap. 37.</p>
            <p>Nay he did not ſtick to pronounce <hi>Anathema to every one, who thinketh, that the grace of God is not only neceſſary every hour, and every moment, but to every act of ours, and they that go about to deny it, ſhall be puniſhed for evermore.</hi> ibid. cap. 2.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Auguſtin</hi> notwithſtanding theſe plauſible expreſſions of <hi>Pelagius,</hi> for the neceſſity of grace, as to its being an <hi>adjutory,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diligenter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogandus eſt Pelagius quam dicat gratiam, quâ fateatur homines adju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vari</hi> ep, 95. <hi>ad Innocent Quaerimus qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> auxilio dicat liberum adju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vart arbitriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? quâ grariâ con, Pelag, &amp; Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt, l,</hi> 1 <hi>c.</hi> 31.</note> Is not at all ſatiſfied, But ſaith that <hi>Pelagius</hi> is * <hi>diligently to be asked what grace he meaneth, and with what grace he acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth (if at leaſt he doth acknowledge the help of grace) that men are helped, against ſinning, and to live righteouſly,</hi> Ep. 95. <hi>And we demand</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>what that aid, and ſuccour is, with which free-will is helped, and with what grace.</hi> And becauſe <hi>Pelagius</hi> would not acknowledge the <hi>adiutory of grace,</hi> by way of an <hi>invincible, and indeclinable working of good in us, Auſtin</hi> truly tels <hi>Pelagius,</hi> that he attributes no more to <hi>Gods working,</hi> notwithſtanding all his aſſertions, that grace is an <hi>adintory</hi> to good, <hi>then he will allow to Satan, in exciting men to evill by his ſinfull ſuggeſtions. And the ſame father ſaith,</hi> that <hi>there is a twofold adiutory to good, the one without which a good work is not
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:115038:31"/>done,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cur non dix. iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>inem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ei gratiâ in bon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m excitari ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ut dixiſti di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aboli ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onibus incitari. Cont. a.</hi> ep. <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l.</hi> cap. 19. <hi>Aliudeſt ad. jutorium ſine qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> aliqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, &amp; altud eſt adjut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rium quo aliquid fit. Cor. &amp; gra. cap.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>p</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5. <hi>Anſ.</hi>
                  </note> the other by and through which a thing is done.</hi> The <hi>Pelagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in granting the former,</hi> never ſatisfied <hi>Auſtin,</hi> becauſe denying (as I fear you do) the latter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe men have exchanged the fathers adint<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rium into their own compulſorium, for me I never denied, but alwaies have aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the neceſſity of grace, by way of adiutory, only the neceſſitation or compulſion of grace is no article of my Creed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. You here falſely and impudently accuſe the ſubſcribers (for thoſe I ſuppoſe you underſtand by that venerable title of <hi>theſe men.</hi>)</p>
            <p n="2">2. With the ſame integrity and modeſty you excuſe your ſelf. A word or two to each.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For your accuſation brought againſt the ſubſcribers of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changing (as you word it) the fathers <hi>adjutorium</hi> into their own <hi>compulſorium</hi> firſt, for the <hi>lectio</hi> In what garden of autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity did you gather that flower of <hi>elegancy,</hi> to <hi>exchange one thing into another,</hi> had you ſaid they have exchanged the <hi>adi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry</hi> for the <hi>compulſory,</hi> or thus, they have changed the <hi>adjutory</hi> into the <hi>compulſory,</hi> though the matter had been <hi>baſe,</hi> yet the ſenſe had been <hi>currant,</hi> but now this expreſſion of (<hi>exchanging into</hi>) makes the whole ſentence not of ſo much worth as braſſe <hi>ſilvered</hi> over, 'Twas a miſtake of <hi>permutare</hi> for <hi>mut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re,</hi> and I ſhould adviſe you to ſtudy that <hi>eaſy work,</hi> where you ſhall finde <hi>Nil per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mumbis Emeſve,</hi> before you adventure again upon the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> had another taken you in this groſſe <hi>non-ſenſe,</hi> he would have ſent you to the <hi>Children,</hi> but I ſpare you.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That you might blaſt and diſgrace, the <hi>infallibility</hi> of the working of grace, you charge the Miniſters with owning the <hi>compulſion</hi> of the will; but this is refuted by being recited, ſo notoriouſly falſe is it; though your <hi>calendar</hi> will not ſpeak them <hi>Saints,</hi> yet your <hi>School</hi> accounts ſome of them <hi>leearned;</hi> Think you that they would all (for now at laſt you have taken in the whole number of 52.) ſpeak ſuch a <hi>contradiction,</hi> That men are willing, and yet compelled? name one of the ſubſcribers, nay any one <hi>proteſtant writer,</hi> that doth not aſſert the <hi>freedome of the will of man in his threefold eſtate of creation, corruption, and reparation,</hi> comprehending both gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> and glory; They will not (I am confident) more deny <hi>freedome of will in man, then
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:115038:31"/>they will reaſon in man,</hi> Which of the Miniſters ever held, that the motions of man in any actions, either naturall, morall, or ſupernaturall were either from <hi>naturall neceſſiity,</hi> or <hi>externall co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action?</hi> Or that all men good, and bad, <hi>hoc ipſo</hi> that they <hi>will,</hi> do not will freely? the will would ceaſe to be it ſelf, ſhould it ceaſe to be free.</p>
            <p>To whatſoever object it is carried. it is not without the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding counſell of the practicall <hi>judgement;</hi> The will being a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall appetite, never moveth but <hi>per modum judicij,</hi> upon ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of ſome goodneſſe to which it moves;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Neceſſe eſt ut cum volumus libcro veli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us arbitrio Arg. de Civ. Dei l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 10. <hi>Liberum arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trium uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ade<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in peccatore<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on perijt, ut per il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lud peccet, max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ime omnes qui cum delectatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ne pec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d cont.</hi> 2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p, Pet, <hi>l.</hi> 1, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Spec. Schol, Or, tho.</hi> c. 19. Par, 6</note> Nor is it in any motions compulſorily over-ſwayed, but worketh accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to its own proper motion, and to the condition of its own nature.</p>
            <p>The moſt wicked man living is ſo far from being without free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, that by his <hi>free-will he ſins, eſpecially th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe that ſin, with delight,</hi> as ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and the more ſinfull men are the more freely they ſin;</p>
            <p>As for the motions of the will in renewed perſons to any thing that is ſupernaturally good, they are ſo far from being without freedome of will, that if their wills did not work freely they ſhould not work holily, their works could not be good, If their workings were not free and the better any action is the more free it is.</p>
            <p>The Theorem then of <hi>Paulus Ferrius</hi> is approve,d who ſaith, <hi>Liberum arbitrium non corrumpitur quoad agendi radicem, ſed quoad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erminum;</hi> That there is in man the nature, and being of <hi>free will</hi> is one thing, but that this naturall <hi>free-will,</hi> unles re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed is able to will a <hi>ſupernaturall good,</hi> is another thing. That the ſpirit of grace doth not take away the liberty <hi>of the will,</hi> which cometh by Gods creation is certain: and that it doth and muſt take away the pravity of the will which ariſeth from mans corruption, before ever a man can will, holily, is moſt certain.</p>
            <p>The will in moving to ſupernaturrll good moveth freely, but to this it muſt be enabled by the efficacious <hi>communion, and adſpiration of the ſpirit of liberty.</hi> Enabled (I ſay) not <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently compelled,</hi> for <hi>compulſion</hi> would deſtroy it, nor <hi>barely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated,</hi> For <hi>ſuaſio moralis</hi> (poor <hi>morall perſwaſion</hi>) cannot reach it.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:115038:32"/>
            <p>Nor dare the ſubſcribers maintain ſuch a freedome <hi>of will,</hi> as that, putting all the operations of grace that may be put, or need to be put into the ballance, a mans naturall free-will, muſt turn the ſcales, and determine the caſe, whether a man ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, or no; accept of grace, or refuſe grace, for this were to attribute more to mans will then to God in converſion, Man ſhould be a convert, not becauſe God made him ſo, but becauſe he would be ſo: God only perſwading, and helping, but man obeying and conſenting.</p>
            <p>Certainly in this reſpect, as <hi>free-will</hi> hath no ability to move a man to be converted, ſo neither when God affords <hi>his effectuall grace,</hi> hath it any ſtrength to hinder a man from converſion; but is brought on, as ſolely, ſo irreſiſtibly by the power of grace; Tis well expreſſed by your Patron M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Bucer, God doth by his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſo demonſtrate life to the mindes of men, that they cannot but yeeld themſelves to God with willingneſſe; they are ſo free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly drawn, that they cannot be carried to any thing with greater ardency, and yet ſo powerfully, that they cannot but follow moſt willingly;</hi> In your next I pray let me know wherein all this while we lay a compulſory upon the will. Nay this efficacious determination of the will by grace, is a moſt happy <hi>adiutory</hi> to it, taking nothing away, but the pravity and rebellion of it, but preſerving, and reſtoring its true liberty. <hi>Gratia non mactat, ſed ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nctificat, non tollit, ſed attollit liberum arbitrium: Grace ſlaieth it not, but ſanctifieth, taketh not away, but elevateth free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will. Grace only ſlaieth the Ram the pravity of the will, but it ſaveth the Iſaac, the naturall liberty alive.</hi> The <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> tempering its working to the diſpoſition of the will, that it may act with ſuch liberty, as becomes its own nature, and <hi>by grace</hi> never be deſtroyed, but perfected; Now if this ſweetly efficacious inſluence of grace be the compulſory you charge the ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers the fathers <hi>Auguſtine, Hierom, Prosper, Bernard,</hi> &amp;c. were for a compu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ory too; It would make a volume to cite all the paſſages that might be taken one of them to this purpoſe. Let a few ſuffice.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſemel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tor poteſtate quae mibi data eſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t liber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n ſervetur arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trium aut ſi al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriu op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o deſtruetur in me libertas arb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>trij; Qui bee dicit qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> excedit bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>phe miam que bereticorun venena non ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>er. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d eteſiph.</hi> c 3.</note> 
               <hi>He who ſaith that the help of grace, upon the will, destroy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the liberty of the will, exceeds a blaſphemer: and is the moſt poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonous of all bereticks,</hi> Hierom.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:115038:32"/>
            <p>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Subventum eſt infirmitati Voluntatis humanae, ut di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinâ gratiâ m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>declinabiliter, &amp; inſeparabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ageretur. Infirmis ſerva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vit, ut ipſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nante invic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſime quod bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numeſt vellent de cor. &amp; gra. <hi>cap</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>Mans infirmitie was ſo relieved, that it ſhould be acted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>declinably, and inſeparably by the grace of god, He reſerved for thoſe that were weak, that they ſhould by his gift will what is good moſt invincibly.</hi> Aug.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Haec</hi> gratia a nullo duro corde respuitur ideo quippe tribuitur ut cordis duriti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> primitus auſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur. de <hi>Praed. cap.</hi> 8.</note> 
               <hi>The grace of God is rejected by no hard heart for it is given to this end that the hardneſſe of the heart may be firſt taken away.</hi> Id.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Voluntas hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mana gratiâ non tollitur ſed ex ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a mutatur in b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam. Aug. degr. &amp; <hi>l. ar</hi> c 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>The will of man is not by grace taken away, but by grace, of evill, changed into good.</hi> Id.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Deus operatur non tantum veras revelationes, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d &amp; bon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates, de grat. cap. 20.</note> 
               <hi>God doth not only diſcover what is true to us, but makes our wills to be good.</hi> Id.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Ex nolen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fficit volentes. cont. a. ep. <hi>Pel l</hi> 1. c. 9</note> 
               <hi>Of unwilling he maketh willing.</hi> Id.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Certum eſt voluntatem noſt üm requiri ad hoc ut bene operemur, ſed illam non h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bemus ex noſtris viribus, ſed Deus operatur in nobis ut v. limus. Aug. de Grat. &amp; <hi>lib.</hi> cap. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Our will is required to our working well, but we have it not from our own power, but God worketh in us to will.</hi> Id.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Certum eſt nos velle cum volum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, ſed ille facit u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> velimus <hi>&amp;c.</hi> praebendo vires <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fficaciſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas voluntati. de <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a, &amp; l.</hi> c. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Its certain that when we are willing we areſo, but God it is that makes us willing,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>by affording most effectuall strength to our wills,</hi> &amp;c. Id.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Deo volenti laſvum facere nullum humanum reſiſtit arbitrium de Cor. &amp; Gra c. 14.</note> 
               <hi>When God wills a mans ſalvation, no free will of man is able to reſist him,</hi> Id.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <p>Non moribus illi (ſcil. gratiae) fit mora non cauſis anceps ſuſpenditur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llis, <hi>Prosp.</hi> de in Grat. c. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>Gratia—mutans int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s mentem, atque reformans<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Vaſque novum ex fracto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ens virtu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e creandi <hi>Proſp.</hi> de ingrat. cap 14.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>une it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>que affectum, quo fumunt mortua vitam, quo teneb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ae fiunt lumen, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſcunt, Nemo al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>j dat, nemo ſibi, <hi>cap,</hi> 15. —Nec habet quiſquam quo ſurg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e poſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Ad vitam ſacro niſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urſum naſc tur ortu.</p>
                  <p>Omnes hanc <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>acultatem in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llo amiſimus in quo omnes peccavimus unde al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> creatione alio que principio renovar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> egemus in Chriſto in quo ſumus nova creatura<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>Proſp<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Reſp,</hi> ad ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Gal.</hi> cap. 6.</p>
               </note> It would be endleſſe to cite all that pertinently might be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to this purpoſe, out of him, as alſo <hi>Proſper</hi> and <hi>Bernard,</hi> the former whereof tels us that <hi>grace cannot by any cauſes what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever be ſuſpended, or be made uncertain. That it changeth the minde. That it faſhions us anew by a power of creation.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:115038:33"/>
            <p>I ſhould gladly be informed what the Miniſters hold tending more toward a <hi>compulſory</hi> then theſe fathers here,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Immittendo honam cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivnem nos praevenit, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutando etiam m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>m volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem ſibi per conſenſum ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git,</hi> Betn, <hi>Tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> de Grat. &amp; lib. Arb. Sion Col.</hi> viſited <hi>p.</hi> 25. <hi>Auſ.</hi>
               </note> and in hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of other places have written.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee how I have made <hi>Prosper</hi> ſpeak; you could not.</p>
            <p n="2">2. You labour to clear your ſelf in theſe words, <hi>for me I never denied, but alwaies have aſſerted the neceſſity of grace by way of adjutory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pelagius</hi> (as hath been ſhewed you) ſaid ſo too, and with much more ſeeming fervency then, and (for ought I know) with as much integrity as your ſelf, Think not by pretending the name of <hi>grace,</hi> to overthrow it in the <hi>efficacy, and truth</hi> of it, only for avoiding more deteſtation among men, as <hi>Pelagius</hi> did;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Grati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> voca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> bulo frangens invidiaw, oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſionem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinans. Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, cont.</hi> Pel. <hi>&amp; Caeleſt, l,</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 37</note> I expect a more clear and diſtinct expreſſion of your ſelf, then barely to ſay, I acknowledge that grace is an <hi>auxiliary,</hi> or <hi>adjutory,</hi> what kinde of <hi>adiutory</hi> mean you? I deſire to know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you mean that grace is an adjutory by way of influence into the will, or by way of concourſe unto the work only, as two men that between them both carry a burthen, yeeld aſſiſtance to each other, neither of them contributing ſtrength unto the other<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And if you do acknowledge, that grace is an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jutory to the will by way of influence into it, whether mean you that this influence is <hi>moralis, ſuaſory</hi> by way of intreatie that the will would move, Or, <hi>Phyſica,</hi> that is properly, <hi>really and efficaciouſly</hi> operative upon it. and if you grant the latter, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe whether grace be an <hi>adiutory uncertain,</hi> and <hi>reſiſtible,</hi> ſo that the will hath power either to accept of grace or refuſe it, or whether grace be an <hi>invincible, infallible, determinating ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iutory</hi> to the will, ſo that it hath no power to render the motions of grace in effectuall to it ſelf, all the requifite motions of grace being afforded. If you grant, that <hi>grace</hi> is <hi>certain, infallible,</hi> and <hi>determinative</hi> in its operation upon the will. I deſire laſtly to know whether you mean that this <hi>invincibility,</hi> and <hi>infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> of the working of grace, be only to be lookt upon as ſuch <hi>reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectu eventus,</hi> in regard of what <hi>doth fall out,</hi> and <hi>de facto</hi> doth come to paſſe, or whether the certain determination of the will by grace, proceedeth from the powerfull nature of that grace of God which as <hi>Austin</hi> ſaith, <hi>no hard heart is able to refuſe:</hi> untill I clearly underſtand your minde in theſe particulars, the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:115038:33"/>pretending of the adjutory of grace in the generall, renders you but ſuſpected in the thoughts of the moſt, and truly ſatisfactory to none.</p>
            <p>The reſidue of the ſoil in your Pamphlet is ſo light and ſandy for the ſubiect (as for the manner of handling any ſubject it is ſuch all over) that now my pen will plough apace.</p>
            <p>I firſt meet with a long winded ſentence, conſiſting of above ten lines, which is a <hi>complication</hi> of falſities, reproaches, and non-ſence: If I can diſcern any thing through a <hi>fog</hi> of words,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſited <hi>p.</hi> 25, <hi>Anſw.</hi>
               </note> it hath ſomething like theſe particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is the calamity of theſe times to iudge truth, and errour, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſurable with the votes of the Miniſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The calamity of the times</hi> is, in that we do not judge truth and errour <hi>commenſurable</hi> with the vote of the Scripture, Such ſecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries as your ſelf have thrown away that <hi>meaſure,</hi> that ſo you might trade in your ware-houſe with the greater advantage, and inſtead thereof you make uſe of a falſe meaſure, your own imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, My ſoul pitties your cheated chapmen! But how is it you will not have truth, and errour commenſurable with the vote of the Miniſters? If M. <hi>Goodwins</hi> vote be not the ſtanding <hi>meaſure</hi> of truth, and errour, for his followers, what is? I am ſure (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his principles) the <hi>written word</hi> cannot be it;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. <hi>p.</hi> ult.</note> for that <hi>is not the word of God;</hi> Name a third meaſure Sir, but if it ſhould happen to be an <hi>Enthuſiaſme,</hi> I ſhall expect but a faint proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your ingagement againſt <hi>quaeriſme</hi> (as you call it) or ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king which (you ſay) you are <hi>now oppoſing in your publike Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery</hi>) And I beleeve that you are doing ſo, as truly as you are oppoſing <hi>Antiſcripturiſme,</hi> and <hi>Manicheiſme,</hi> the former whereof you patronize, and the latter you underſtand not, as I have proved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>They have engroſſed the honour and reputation of being Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox unto themſelves.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſited. <hi>p.</hi> 25. <hi>Anſ.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>You grieve that others ſhould be <hi>reputed Orthodox</hi> alone, without you, but why do you not grieve that others <hi>ſhould be Orthodox</hi> alone, with you, <hi>Reality</hi> is better then <hi>Reputation,</hi> and 'tis better to <hi>be</hi> then to be <hi>accounted Orthodox:</hi> And as for <hi>honour,</hi> that will flie from you, as long as you flie from <hi>honeſty,</hi> Intreat God to give you the heart of an Orthodox Miniſter, and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:115038:34"/>you will ſoon have the honour of ſuch an one; otherwiſe know that your preſent diſhonour is nothing to your future ſhame, either to <hi>poſterity,</hi> or <hi>eternity.</hi> Think upon it in time, 'tis friendly advice,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>They</hi> (the Miniſters,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſited <hi>p.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.</note> ſtill) <hi>ſquare their votes concerning truth' and errour by the traditions of the Elders</hi> (he meaneth the Fathers.)</p>
            <p>If you be not for <hi>traditions,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> you are for nothing; ſince you have thrown off the <hi>written word.</hi> For ought I know <hi>tradition</hi> is the beſt <hi>flower</hi> in your garden; but charge not the Miniſters with being for any <hi>traditions,</hi> but written; and for theſe I confeſſe they are ſo zealous, that for your oppoſing them they have deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly placed you in the <hi>forlorn</hi> of the <hi>erroneous.</hi> And ſcoff not too much at the <hi>Elders.</hi> I knew the time (even when you were writing the preceeding page) that you would fain have been <hi>beholding to them;</hi> And could you then have perſwaded thoſe Elders to have bleſt you with but one tradition, you would not now have blaſted the tradition of the Elders: But now you are like a <hi>beggar</hi> who when he cannot prevail for an alms, goeth away railing; But I marvell how the <hi>younger,</hi> I mean <hi>Bucer</hi> and <hi>Ball,</hi> eſcape your reviling. They were as far from <hi>pitying you,</hi> and as forward in <hi>chaſtiſing you</hi> as the Elders; I ſhall add, Some of <hi>Pelagius's</hi> friends may haply take it ill at your hands, that when you were ſhooting reproaches among the Elders, you did not deſire your Patron <hi>Pelagius</hi> to ſtand aſide; Sir, to be ſhort with you; the Miniſters ſometimes <hi>uſe</hi> but never <hi>depend</hi> upon the <hi>traditions of the Elders,</hi> One of the beſt <hi>traditions</hi> that ever I learned from any of the <hi>Elders</hi> was from <hi>Tertullian,</hi> and 'tis this, <hi>Custome without truth is but the antiquity of errour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your next paſſage breaths a malice ranklie ſavouring of <hi>athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſme,</hi> Your book goeth out like a ſnuff, and now fumeth with nothing but reproaches againſt the <hi>government of Chriſt, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanation of Scripture,</hi> and <hi>elevation of your ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Miniſters of the Province of London,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſited p. 25.</note> cannot but be full of this information that there was more of the truth and power of Religion in England, under the Praelaticall government then in all the reformed Churches beſides, The beſt ſucceſſe unto which they can with any colour of truth, entitle this government, is but
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:115038:34"/>the ſucceſſe of gardiners ſheers, which prosper only by the ſnip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping off, and keeping under thoſe thriving branches which elſe would out-grow their fellows.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſay that travellers <hi>have fild</hi> the Miniſters of <hi>London,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> with <hi>information,</hi> but there's one that I fear hath fild you with this (among a great deal of other) falſe <hi>information.</hi> I fear 'tis he that is the greateſt <hi>traveller, and the greateſt liar in the world.</hi> The Lord rebuke thee <hi>Satan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For your telling us that the <hi>praelaticall government was more bleſt with the power of religion, then any reformed Church:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrâ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>gebit ingebe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> I know not why you mention it, unleſſe it be to make <hi>Satan</hi> ſport, as if you were his jeſter, Or to give <hi>aquavitae</hi> to <hi>Antichriſt</hi> in his <hi>fainting fits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Was the power of religion more under <hi>praelaticall govornment</hi> then in any <hi>reformed Churches?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here's a good commendation (in the mean time) for <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent Churches,</hi> for praelaticall government had more religion, you ſay then <hi>ALL</hi> the <hi>Reformed Churches;</hi> And if ſo, I ſay then <hi>Independent Churches</hi> too, unleſſe you will evade my argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by ſaying that <hi>Independent Churches</hi> were not then <hi>formed,</hi> or if they were <hi>formed,</hi> were not <hi>reformed,</hi> ſo well as the prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laticall but ſo as you may ſcratch <hi>Preſbytery,</hi> you care not though you <hi>wound</hi> your ſelf.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Why tell you not the reader that <hi>the power of religion</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed in the daies of <hi>no government,</hi> as well as it <hi>thrived</hi> in the da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es of <hi>praelaticall government,</hi> you were afraid the Reader would have drawn this concluſion thence. Its better with Religion when people are ſuffered to do no more then the <hi>Praelates</hi> will, then when they are ſuffered to do as much as themſelves will.</p>
            <p>The ſpeaking of the whole truth would have laid <hi>your way</hi> as <hi>low,</hi> as it raiſeth <hi>praelacy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. What <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> informed you of ſuch a decay of <hi>the power of religion,</hi> in all the reformed Churches, as that <hi>England</hi> did ſo much exceed them? I bleſſe God for what I have ſeen in <hi>Exg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> and I magnifie his name for what I have <hi>read and heard</hi> from other <hi>reformed Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we went before them in ſome things, haply they might have the precedency in other; I ſuppoſe it is with Churches as
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:115038:35"/>with Chriſtians, God variouſly diſpenſeth his graces, he beſtows upon ſome an eminency in one, upon others in another haply they might hold forth a clearer torch to diſcover <hi>Antichriſt</hi> then we, and peradventure it might burn hotter then ours, And its likely on the other ſide that for <hi>practicals,</hi> many of ours at home might excell them, and our walkings might be more even. I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved ſometimes that a man who followeth a torch, walks more ſteadily and not in ſo much danger of ſtumbling, as he who car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth it, Sir, I ſhould not much contend about your commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>power of religion,</hi> under <hi>prelacy;</hi> did I but ſee you ſo to recollect the former <hi>power of Religion</hi> as to be humbled for the preſent <hi>weakneſſe</hi> of it, and to reſolve that weakneſſe into its <hi>proper cauſe,</hi> I mean, a <hi>toleration</hi> of all ungodlineſſe and abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble opinions.</p>
            <p n="4">4. You that commend <hi>prelacy</hi> as being bleſt with the <hi>power of Religion,</hi> I pray tell me, whether was this <hi>power of religion,</hi> upheld and preſerved by any goodneſſe in the <hi>pralaticall govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> or did God only make it an occaſion to drive his people cloſer to himſelf by their perſecutions and unquietneſſe in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward reſpects, and haply by ſinfull impoſitions; If the latter be true, that praelacie only were ſuch an accidentall occaſion of the power of religion, you might as well for ought I know have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended the greateſt enemies of the Church, and have commended the fitneſſe of <hi>Potiphars</hi> houſe for <hi>Joſeph:</hi> but why do you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare Praelacie to a governmnt that God hath bleſſed, even when it hath been (in a manner) under perſecution, and ſavoured only of Eccleſiaſticall mildneſſe, not medling with the purſe or the body, but tending to recover the ſoul and oppoſe ſin.</p>
            <p>If the former be true, that the power of religion was from the goodneſſe of praelacy as its cauſe, you have then quite undone <hi>Independency</hi> which is never like by <hi>Anarchy</hi> the quite contrary to <hi>Pralacy,</hi> to produce the ſame effect of the power of religion.</p>
            <p>For that your horrid expreſſion that the only ſucceſſe of the <hi>Preſbyteriall government,</hi> is to ſnipp off forward branches; I told you even now who the traveller was that fild you with this information. A falſehood ordinarily palpable maketh its refuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion eaſy, but when in falſity it is aſtoniſhing, the hearer cannot but a while ſuſpend his reply. It fared thus with me in reviewing
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:115038:35"/>this paſſage; Is it poſſible (thought I) that a man who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends not only to be a Chriſtian, but a Miniſter, ſhould thus far throw off both? but I lookt upon you as the <hi>non-ſuch</hi> of your way, and ſo I recollected my thoughts into the way of an anſwer, I would know who are the forward branches that the ſheers of <hi>Preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery</hi> ſnipp off? Are they fruitfull branches, or are they not rather ſuckers, who draw away that nouriſhment from others which might make them fruitfull and convert it into thriving in hereſies, in Atheiſme, and unholy opinions. If ſo, I ſee no reaſon but the throwing away the ſheers would be the overthrowing of the plant.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſit. p. 6. <hi>Anſ.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An evill eye upon the Parliament is no diſſenting character of the Genius of the Ministers of London</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Me thinkes theſe words are hardly ſence, but I have taken you tripping ſo often that I ſhall not now be rigid. Your meaning is, The <hi>London. Miniſters</hi> have an evill eye upon the Parliament.</p>
            <p>The Parliament hath ſuffered (with grief I ſpeak it) ever ſince Sectaries would needs be their advocates. It was better with them when you wrote your <hi>Theomachia,</hi> Accuſe not the Miniſters of an evill eye, toward the Parliament, If your eyes be good toward them, I am ſure they are lately cured, The Reader knows by what eye ſalve.</p>
            <p>What remains of this weak Pamphlet conſiſts of nothing but three or four prophanations of Scripture,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sion. Col</hi> viſit. p. 26.</note> and ſome four or five nauſeous commendations of the Authour and book.</p>
            <p>For the former you ſay that <hi>the reaſon why your pen moved againſt its accuſers rather then your fellow-hereticks, was becauſe Chriſt ſaith the ſtones would cry if the honour of Chriſt ſhould not be vindicated:</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> and you ſay <hi>you were loth that the ſtones and tiles ſhould take this honour from you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There's not an errour tranſcribed out of your books, but tends to the high <hi>diſhonour</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the deniall of his Scriptures, of his grace, and for your perſiſting in theſe, <hi>The ſtones indeed might ſpeak,</hi> though not for you, but againſt you. 'Tis a miracle the ſtones and tiles of the houſes do not ſpeak about the ears of one ſo prophane and erroneous.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I bear my charge upon my ſhoulder, with more then patience,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſit. <hi>p</hi> 26.</note> even with joy.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:115038:36"/>
            <p>I admire more the patience of God in forbearing to puniſh you,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> then yours in bearing your paniſhment and let me hear of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for ſin, before you tell m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> again of joy in your ſorrows.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The two theeves had not ſuffered death,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sion Col.</hi> viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>p</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> but to colour over the crucifying of Chriſt, and no teſtimony had been given at this time againſt the hereſies of the other, had not the</hi> 52. <hi>judged it expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent that my name ſhould be blaſted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I doubt whether the compariſon between your ſelf and Chriſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anwſ.</hi>
               </note> ſavours not of blaſphemous arrogancy; A parallel between your fellow-heretickes who have rob'd God of his glory, and <hi>theeves</hi> would have held good; had it been between your ſelf and them, it would have been better: but could you make <hi>it</hi> between your ſelf and the penitent thief, it would be beſt of all. I wiſh that what you write in the end of your book a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>erra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> could admit of this charitable conſtruction of your repentance, The words are theſe, For <hi>Excuſabilis</hi> you deſire the Reader to read <hi>Inexcuſabilis,</hi> however I ſhall add this, the trueſt ſentence in all your book is this which you place among your errours. ⁂</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
